<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>NO TITLE</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>No publication information is avaliable</p>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Produced by: Adobe Acrobat 8.12 Paper Capture Plug-in</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Generated from a source PDF document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date>2002-11-08T02:05:07 -0500</date>
	      Created by: Acrobat Capture 3.0</creation>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-06-19T04:51:00 -0400</date>
<respStmt>
<name>unknown person</name>
</respStmt>
<item>unknown changes</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 id="page_1" n="1" type="page">
<p>THE TUFTS DAILY
~reYou Read It First
Monday, November 29, 1999 Volume XXXIX, Number 531
tionshipwith FletcherdeanJohn
Galvin. ThetwometwhenGalvin
was an Anny general in Latin
AmericaandworkedwithBrad~
ley ona numberofprojects on a
variety offoreign policy issues.
BradleyjsfigJ,lting.to.wrest
the presidentialnominationfrom
Democratic favorite Vice Presi 
dentAI Gore. Gore's staffisre~
portedly in the process oftrying
to showthatllr~dIeyis not
knowledgeable regarding for 
eignaffairs.
With this in mind, the event
willbe organized in orderto give
Bradley an opportunityto dem 
onstrate his knOWledge and ex 
perience on a variety offoreign
policy and international issues.
Instead of a conventional lec 
ture format, the speech is
planned as a question and an 
swer session with Tufts stu 
dents.
Bradley's presentation was
organized directly through the
FletcherSchool. TheTufts Stu 
dents for Bill Bradley group,
however, willbeaiding Bradley's
staff in assuring that the event
runs smoothly, accordingto Ann
Maurer, the group's campus or 
ganizer.
"I'mreally excitedthatBrad 
ley chose Tufts to unveil his
foreign policy, notonlybecause
itputsTuftsinthenatiopallime 
light, but also because there are
a lot of Bradley supporters at
Tufts," she said.
AlthougJ,l plans have been in
the offmg for weeks, Bradley's
attendance remained uncertain
untilFriday,Nov. I9whenTerry
Ann Knopf, Fletcher School
publicist, receivedconfrrmation
that he would, in fact, speak at
Tufts.
AND MOREt PAGE 5
TODAY IN ARTS:
-Celebrate Bill Bradley's visit with the Dailyts top ten
political movies
Dailyfile photo
Bradley, seen here with campus organizer Ann Maurer
at MIT in October, will speak today in Cohen Auditorium
at 1 p.m.
Bradley shoots for student support
byBROOKEMENSCHEL
Daily Editorial Board
Campus will beabuzz todayas
nationalmediaandpoliticians Ven 
turew Tufts to hear presidential
can{jigateBiIlBradley'srtluchan 
ticipated first foreigilpolicy ad 
dress..'IheformerNewJerseysena 
tor is expected to bring a media
circus to. Tufts with him as he
discloses his policy for the first
time this afternoon.
Bradley is expected to assert
that it is of key importance for
Americathatgoods, services, and
ideas are able to be exchanged
freely withothernations, TheNew
York Timesreportedyesterday. One
ofthe key points ofBradley's for 
eign policy program is thatall na 
tions, from the pooresttothe rich 
est, can benefit from increased
trade and technology. These
changes would encourage further
spreadofdemocracy world-wide.
Bradley will speak today in
Cohen Auditorium at 1 p.m. The
auditorium has the capacityto hold
approximately 700 people. A por 
tion ofCohen will be reserved for
the local and national press, while
therestofthe seatswill be filled by
Tufts undergraduates, graduate
students, and faculty.
Tickets are available to stu 
dents, free of charge, at the
Aidekman box office from 9 a.m.
until noon or until the supply is
exhausted. Jacksongymwill have
over-flowaccommodations,avail 
able to students once no tickets
remain for Cohen. Seating in Jack 
son will be frrst come, frrst serve.
The FletcherSchoolofLawand
Diplomacy was chosen as the lo 
cation for Bradley's speech, en 
titled "American Leadership in a
Rapidly Changing World," be 
cause of his long standing rela-
Bradley to deliver
first foreign affairs
talk at Tufts today
Foreign policy unveiled through
question and answer with students
to run the city council. ... It's nine people who have
to work together to accomplish anything. In a sense,
it's not my job to represent the community. I do not
pretend to represent the electorate - I orchestrate
the actions ofa committee."
The day-to-day functions ofthe 100,000-person
city are monitored by a City Controller, a salaried
worker, leaving the council free to deal with larger
issues, among them zoning laws and the finer points
ofthe school system.
Referring to azoning law passed duringhis tenure
after a tough battle within the council, Duehay said,
"ifI could take you for a walk through Cambridge, I
could point out house after house, development after
development, store after store, that has been posi 
tively affected by this law."
In keeping with the theme of the class itself,
Duehay gave his thoughts on leadership methods
and styles in local government, illustrating the ideas
with examples from his own experience.
"There are always leaders and followers," he
began. "Now, there are traditional followers, who go
along silently with what the leader tells them, and
there are courageous followers," who he said ac 
tively participate in furthering the ideas ofthe leader
they support. "Idon'tthink there are many traditional
followers anymore... I don't think there are people
who follow blindly anymore.
"Mostpeople don'tgetthe opportunityto be a US
Senator," he continued, "but thousands of people
are involved in local government. In a place like
Cambridge, you often don't have enough money to
pay [staffers]. So you need to go out and convince
them that you're the person that they want to work
for. An elected leader really has to earn the confi 
dence ofthe pt:ople who work for them." .
One of the most difficult tasks Duehay has as
mayor is motivating the various constituencies to
both work in the community, and to come outto vote.
Among these, one ofthe most difficult is the student
population.
"It'svery hard work; Harvard makes it incredibly
difficult to reach students because they don't pub 
lish their studentaddresses." In an effortto motivate,
Duehay often tries to address issues traditionally
associatedwith the student population, among them,
the T's hours ofoperation and the development of
local hangoutareas like Harvard and Central squares.
"Ina place like Cambridge, the studentscouldtake
overthe city ifthey wanted to-butthey don't want
to."
CaDlbridge Dlayor comes to
give his thoughts on leadership
by DANIELBARBARISI
Daily Editorial Board
Tufts has never had the best relationship with the
surroundingcommunitiesofSomerville and Medford,
an issue revisited each year when trouble arises
between students and local residents. Just a little
ways down Mass. Ave., however, lies a university
with quite the opposite relationship - Harvard is
Cambridge, in aunique way that makes Cambridge a
town unlike any other. Last Wednesday, a small
group ofTufts students were able to see what makes
Cambridge tick from the mouth of its leader and
spokesman, city Mayor Frank Duehay.
Mayor for a two-year term ending in January,
Duehay came to campus to speak to 14 freshmen in
the explorations class entitled, "Leadershipand Group
Dynamics," at the behest ofone ofthe instructors,
Duehay staffer Matt Klainer.
"We've been looking at leadership through a theo 
retical framework, both with current events examples
and historical information,"Klainersaid. "Iaskedhim to
come in ordertogive areal-world perspective, letting us
step out ofthe academic world for a little while and see
how leaders function in the outside world."
A former directorofthe Lincoln-Filene Centerat
Tufts, Duehay had some complaints about the man 
ner in which Tufts deals with the surrounding com 
munities.
"Tufts should be doing better," he said. "We'reall
players in the community, and the communities do
not run themselves alone. I think universities should
be working in a variety of ways with the school
system - In fact, I was recently talking to the new
mayor ofSomerville about it."
Cambridge functions in amanner unlike any other
city - and, as such, Duehay has a job description
different from that of most mayors. Cambridge is
governed by anine membercity council which elects
themayorfrom among its own ranks. Its uniqueness,
however, comes in the manner in which those offi 
cials are elected.
"Cambridge is the only city in the country that
elects its officials by proportional representation,"
he explained. "It's a framework that ensures the
community is more completely and accurately re 
flected than under a plurality system. But in terms of
getting that group to come to terms with each other,
people become very independent, and become more
responsive to the particular group that elected them,
and arguably less responsive to other groups.
"I run the city council. Or," Duehay paused, "I try
ColoDlbia's ongoing 'war against
drug lords debated 4:&gt;n catnpus
Joumalist raises questions ofwhere the responsibility lies
byJENNIFERTAKIGAWA yet unidentified paramilitary fac&#183;&#183; abouthalfoftheworld'ssupplyof
Daily Staff Writer tion. Almost 50 journalists havt: raw coca leaf, one ofthe reasons
In an address entitled"Crisis in been killed in the country sinct: Smyth was opposed to their con 
Colombia," freelance journalist 1989, putting ColombiaaIl)ongtht: tinuedactivity. Following Smyth's
Frank Smyth brought Colombia's most dangerous nations in which lecture, anumberofaudiencemem 
war against drugs home to Tufts to practice journalism, according bel'S used the question and an 
lastweek. Thetalk came only days totheNewYork-basedCommittet: swer period as an opportunity to
before two journalists covering a to Protect Journalists. show their disagreement with
local election in the town of &#163;1 The main ingredient in cocaine, Smyth's views. Tensions ran high
Playon, Colombiawere killed by a coca, is processed in and exported between Smyth and students who
from Colombia, makingthe coun&#183;&#183; did not share his beliefs.
try one of the most significant When talking about drug traf 
battlegrounds in the war against ficking in Colombia, there are two
drugs. Although the US gives $169 wars to be dealt with: the political/
million a year to the Colombian militarywarand the drug war. While
government to combat the drug Smyth's lecture was in the context
trade, Smyth said that most oftht: ofthe drug war, some Colombian
money is diverted to Bogota's audience members argued against
counterinsurgency war against his stance based on their own
leftist guerrillas. personal experiences with the civil
Smyth explainedthe Colombian and political war.
drug trade using a pyramid struc&#183;&#183; Smyth defended himself by
ture. He said thatone integral group saying that he dislikes FARC be-Fiiii=iiii=ii=iiiiiiiiiiii==iiii==iiii~
in the drug trade is the formerly cause it protects the Colombian
pro-Moscow Revolutionary peasants doing the drug process 
ArmedForcesofColombia(FARC). ing.
He put FARC atthe bottomofth(~"I'mchallengingthe notion that
pyramid, since it is at the root of FARC is the center ofthis [drug
the drug trade. Leftist guerrillas war], and I don't think it makes
Photo byDaniel Rodrigues such as FARC allegedly protect
FrankSmyth Colombian peasants who produce see SMYTH, page 2
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_2" n="2" type="page">
<p>2
THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999
Mostly cloudy,
blustery
High: 34
not fighting against communism
anymore," Smyth said.
Colombia is already the fourth
largest recipient ofUS foreign aid
in the world after Israel, Egypt, and
Jordan, making it the largest US
backed counterinsurgency effort
since Vietnam.
Smyth served as an investiga 
tive consultant for Human Rights
Watch, as well as for Amnesty
International, and writes about
drug trafficking for publications
such as The Washington Post,
The Village Voice, The New Re 
public, and The Wall StreetJour-
Tonight
Mostly cloudy,
scattered snow showers
Low: 30
tary in their fight againstthe FARC.
Amid the debate over whether to
escalate US drug-war aid to Co 
lombia, Smyth questioned US bias
against Colombia's leftist guerril 
las such as those in the FARC.
Smyth explained that there are
some, likeGeneral BarryMcCaffrey,
who want to double current US
military aidto provide$600 milIion
to help Colombia defense forces
fight offthe leftist "narco-gueril 
las."
"[The US] still want[s] to back
ourallies, butwecan'ttakeit in the
nameofcommunism becausewe're
Mostly sunny AM,
afternoon flurries
High:41
The DailyWeekday Weather Forecast
lIB Today
~
V
TMS Campus News Service
Sam Mix boughtChristmas gifts
for eightpeople, birthday presents
for five more and some furniture
for her own home, all in an hour
and a half.
Thank cyberspace for e-com 
merce.
After years of schlepping
through packed malls, Mix has
turned to the Internet to avoid
unrulycrowds, frazzled clerks, and
heavy traffic.
"It'schanging my life," declares
Mix, 32, a secretary in a Chicago
Loop office. "E-commerce is the
biggest, greatest thing."
Millions oftraditionalists and
mainline retailers might disagree.
Old-fashioned stores-thosewith
front doors, aisles, and human
clerks - have been crowded all
year, thanks to the booming
economy. Andthey will be packed
even tighter Friday as retailers
heraldthe startofthe holiday shop 
ping season. Across the country,
stores are openingearly, some weIl
before dawn, to accommodatethe
expected throngs.
Still, the embrace of on-line
shopping by Mix and others is
creatinga chaIlenge for brick-and 
mortar stores as they vie for con 
sumerdoIlars. MaIl merchants and
department stores are beefing up
customerservice, offering free gift
wrapping andgivingout deep dis 
counts in an attempt to keep shop 
pers off-line and in line at the cash
registers. Those are smart strate 
gies in light ofthe fact that Internet
analysts say this holiday season
will bethe biggestfor e-commerce
sales. Estimates for on-line shop 
ping between Thanksgiving and
New Year's Dayrange from $4 bil 
lion to $16 billion.
"It's going to be the coming 
out year," said Mark Speaker, co 
author of the Complete Idiot's
Guide to E-Commerce and Presi-
'Tis the season to shop online
Cyberspace is alternative for dorm-bound students
dentofLearnlots.com, an Internet purely a chore for mostpeople but
service that educates companies a form ofentertainment. Internet
about electronic retailing. sites can't replicate the sights and
Speaker, who estimates holi- sounds of Christmas shopping.
day on-line sales will reach $12 Consider the attitude ofAlvin
billion, said web retailers are win- Isacowitz, a touristfrom Brooklyn
ning over consumers for three whowas visiting Chicago's Mag 
chiefreasons: price, convenience, nificent Mile on Wednesday with
and selection. Unlike last year, his wife and young daughters.
Speakersaid, "e-tailers"have rec- Isacowitz said he despises shop 
ognized that they need to address ping but refuses to go on-line to
such concerns as timely delivery, pick outholiday gifts. "I like to see
return policies, and security. it, feel it, mutilate it, and spin it,"
For instance, many on-line saidthebag-laden Isacowitz. "The
stores now guarantee giftdelivery Internet is all flash and no sub 
by Christmas. stance. Plus, it's very difficult to
"Trust has been built on the take your children shopping on
web," he said. "I believe next year the Internet."
people are going to think about George Whalin, President of
shopping on-line first instead of Retail Management Consultants
comparing the two experiences." in San Marcos, Calif., scoffs at the
Not so fast, say brick-and-mor- threat ofe-commerce. "We'renot
tar retailers, who point out that, losing sleep over it," Whalin said.
even with the most optimistic pro- "Retailers are focusing on how to
jections, Internetsaleswill account maximize their sales on people
for only a fraction oftheestimated coming through the doors in the
$185 billion that will be spent in next five weeks."
NovemberandDecember. Accord- Butmanyretailers are pumping
ing to a consumer survey by up sales by plunging into
Deloitte &amp; Touche and the Na- cyberspace with their own sites.
tional Retail Federation, Ameri- In the past year, major companies
cans are expected to spend an such as Toys 'R' Us, Foot Locker,
averageof$849 attraditional stores Target, and Abercrombie &amp; Fitch
this season, a 4.3 percent increase have started on-line stores. And
over 1998. they're attracting .loads of cus-
In otherwords, expectthe usual tomers, said Diane Swonk, chief
mobs to swarm North Michigan economistfor Chicago'sBankOne
Avenue, Woodfield Shopping Corp. "Brick-and-mortarshopsare
Center, and the other malls in and effectivelycompetingagainsttheir
around Chicago on "BlackFriday" cyberspace counterpartsby lever 
- the term retailers have given to agingtheir well-known names and
the traditional start of the shop- puttingdot-com behindthem," she
ping season on the day after said.
Thanksgiving. The term comes With so many companies ca 
from the fact that it often was the teringto the web-savvy customer,
day retailers puttheirbottom lines Sam Mix saidshehardlysteps into
in the black for the year. a traditional store anymore. She
"Noquestion, shoppers will be even orders her groceries on-line
out in force," said Kurt Barnard, via Skokie-based Peapod Inc.
President of Barnard's Retail "My gifts are coming in a big
Trend Report in Upper Montclair, brown sleighthat is the UPS truck,"
N.J. Barnard said shopping isn't she said.
Many students disagree with Smyth's view
SMYTH
- WeatherForcast courtesyofweather.yahoo.com
Today will be mostly sunny in the morning with increasing clouds in the afternoon
and possible sprinkles or flurries later on. The high will be in the lower 40s.
Tonight will be mostly cloudy with scattered snow showers, becoming blustery
later on. The low will be around 30 and the chance of snow is 40 percent.
Tuesday will bring more clouds and a 30 percent chance of snow showers with a
high in the mid 30s. Gee, I hope Andrew comes back soon.
continued from page 1
sense for the US to wipe out the
FARC," he said.
Smyth placed the cartels in 
volved in the exportofcocaon the
top ofthe pyramid.
He went on to say that United
States officials fail to recognize
the mid-portion of his pyramid,
Colombia's right wing
paramilitaries, which are involved
in processing and transportingthe
coca leaves.
Since the 1960s, the US has
beenbacking the Colombian mili-
Two visions ofglobal
economy to collide at
WTOmeeting
SEATTLE-The global economy, or so its boosters proclaim,
is luringthe world into a future offantastic riches-and no country
will enjoy a greater windfall than the United States.
But a growing cadre ofcritics broods over darker visions ofa
sinister, netherworld economy.
The two visions collide this week in Seattle, where representa 
tives ofnearly every nation in the world are converging to launch
a new round ofglobal trade talks that could determine the shape of
the global economy for years to come.
Inside and outside the convention center, delegates and protest 
ers alike will be struggling with the same, overarching question:
Should the rules protect the rights only ofthose who profit from
trade, while ignoringthe manysocial questions that arise from how
goods are made?
"Intellectually, I think it's very difficult to say that we're con 
cerned with property rights, but not the effects oftrade on workers
and the environment," said Alan Wolff, a former deputy US trade
representative and leading trade attorney.
Mainstream economists give globalization - the increasing
flow ofgoods, services, people and money across national borders
- much ofthe credit for boom times in the United States and better
times overseas. Critics, by contrast, see capitalism run amok.
"Human rights, labor rights and environmental rights are being
completely subordinated to the right to make a profit," maintained
Julie Light, managing editorofCorporate Watch, an Internet maga 
zine that is part ofthe growing movement against globalization in
its current form. "There has to be some check on this."
Clinton's lawyer,
&#8226; &#8226;
prIvate eye reunIte as
Bradley boosters
WASHINGTON- PresidentClinton'slawyer and his private eye
haveteamed up again, but, no, he'snot irftrouble. This time it's Vice
President AI Gore getting the bad news.
Robert S. Bennett,Clinton'spersonal lawyer, andTerry Lenzner,
who served the President's legal and political teams by looking into
the backgrounds ofwomen in Clinton's past, are among the hosts
ofafund-raising reception for Democratic presidentialcandidate Bill
Bradley, to be held Dec. 2 in Washington.
Lenzneracknowledgedthattheelection ofBradley,who is known
as the straightest ofarrows, wouldn'tbe very good for his business.
"Butit'd begood for the country," Cenznersaid with a laugh. "Like
most ofthe country, we'd like somebody in the White House who
would not get into the kind ofactivities this President got engaged
in -and he was my client. People want something different."
Lenzner said he met Bradley in 1969, when Lenzner was legal
services directoroftheOffice ofEconomicOpportunity and Bradley
usedhis summerbreakfrom theNew York Knicksto volunteerto help
perform field studies ofantipoverty programs.
News
Briefs
Compiled from the Los Angeles Times-Washington
Post News Service and TMS Campus News Service
Reparations plan
spotlights Holocaust
survivors' plight
NEWYORK-Ina life fi I1ed withunspeakabletragedy, Elizabeth
Roth has found a quiet haven: Once a month, she and other elderly
Holocaust survivors gatherat a smaIl kosherrestaurant in Brooklyn
where they drink coffee, exchange small talk and deal with the
traumatic past on their own terms.
A frail woman who lost her family at Auschwitz, Roth now
wrestles with the medical and psychological burdens ofadvancing
age. The hours she spends at the Coffee House, hosted by a local
Jewish reliefagency, are one ofthe few bright spots in her world.
In recent weeks, however, a cloud has been hovering over these
gatherings. As word spreads of$I.25 billion in assets thattwo Swiss
banks will return to Holocaust victims - an agreement that a court
mayratify this week- Roth and others have learned thatthey must
fill out a long, unwieldy questionnaire to get cash payments of
roughly $500to $1 ,000each.
Onestarkquestion in particularhas awakened painful memories:
"Pleasedescribe, in asmuch detail as you can, where the subjectwas
during the years 1934through 1945," reads item D on page three of
the six-page legal form approved by the US District Court for New
YOlk.
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_3" n="3" type="page">
<p>THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999
3
Features
Karen
Forseter
-----------
'Featuring...
angles on the site.
The service has been available for only a week so
far, just in time for holiday shopping. The Air Fam 
ished iD costs $80, and the Air Turbulence iD costs
$85, both in addition to shipping charges. Estimated
delivery time is between two and three weeks ofthe
completed order. The suggested retail price from the
Nike online store for a regular Air Famished sneaker
is $70, and $75 Air Turbulence. Although the NIKE
iD sneakers are only available for pur 
chase online, returns can be made at
Niketowns or Nike factory stores
nationwide, as
well as by mail.
Only4000rders
fortheNIKE iD
sneakers are ac 
cepted per day,
and the avail 
ability is limited
to the United
States for now. However, the company hopes to
expand its customization operation in the future.
With the growth ofnew technology and the expan 
sion of Nike's infrastructure to accommodate the
deliveryofpersonalized products, the company hopes
to offer more sneakers and other personalized prod 
ucts to meet the needs of customers. The website
states, "while we have big/ideas for the future, we
. recognize that without your participation, we can
only go so far. Your role is as important as ours in
designing and delivering truly personalized prod 
ucts and services."
"NIKE iD brings us back to our roots, when we
designed and sold shoes one-by-oneout of the
trunk ofmy old Plymouth," said Nike Chairman and
CEO Phil Knight in a press release. "We have now
come full circle, using our design and perfor 
mance expertise combined with Internet
technology to offer custom 
ized products. This holi 
day season marks the
first time in our history
that consumers have the
opportunity to literally
leave their mark on a per 
sonalized pairofNike shoes."
Nike hopes to relllain a foot
ahead of the cOlllpetition with
new personalized shoe design
Website allows customers to create their own sneakers
Somerville joins in nationwide campaign
against hate crimes
by KELLY WISNEWSKI
Daily Editorial Board
In an age when so many people display their own
identitieswith vanity license plates and monogrammed
"his and hers" towels, it's no wonder that personal 
ization has reached the clothing industry. Now, Nike
is giving its customers the opportunity to design
their own sneakers.
Anyone who wants to feel like a sports star, with
their own customized sneaker, can visittheNIKE iD
section ofNike'swebsite (www.nike.com)and pur 
chase a personalized pair. Visitors to the site are led
through a personalization process, where different
aspects ofthe sneakerare chosen to their liking. Both
men and women have two choices for the basic model
ofsneaker - either the Air Famished iD for cross
training, or the Air Turbulence 1D for running.
Once a model is picked out, the customerchooses
from a variety ofbase color combinations, and then
chooses an accent color. There are four base color
combinations for the Air Turbulence iD, three base
color combinations for the Air Famished iD, and six
accent colors available for both models. Nike says
that the color limitations are due to technical consid 
erations, material limitations, and because some color
combinations "would be just too darn ugly."
The final step is to submit a personal identifica 
tion, which can be up to eight characters and/or
numbers long. Although Nike gives the customer a
good deal ofleeway as far as choices for a personal
design, the company filters the personal identifica 
tions for offensive material that they do not want
placed on their sneakers. Once customers have fin 
ished their design, they can inspect their creation
from a variety
of
In response to an iricrease in the incidence ofhate crimes across the nation, several cities are joining
together to put a stop to them through a campaign called "No Place for Hate." Recently, the City of
Somervillehas signed on to this campaign, with a pledge to stop hate crimes including vandalism, words
ofdisrespect, harassment, acts ofviolence, and even murder.
State and local leaders gathered on Sept. 27 at the State House in Boston to launch the statewide
campaign. The main goal ofthe No Place for Hate campaign is to set community standards ofrespect
for diversity. Itstrives to end racism, anti-Semitism, and bigotry ofall kinds. The program is sponsored
bythe Anti-Defamation League (ADL), the Massachusetts Municipal Association (MMA), and 50 other
organizations.
"The MMA, on behalfofMassachusetts communities, is grateful to ADL for creating this program
that will give cities and towns an opportunity to make a difference by supporting the primary goals of
the program-awar~nessand understanding," MMA Executive Director Geoffrey C. Beckwith said in
a press release.
Through the program, cities andtowns work toward being declared "No Place for Hate." To participate,
communities must fulfill one mandatory requirement, and then select three otheractivities from a list of
over 30 programs and projects. All ofthis must be completed by Dec. 31,2000.
Some of these activities include anti-bias training for teachers and administrators in city school
systems, and the creation ofsigns displayed at the city hall that symbolize the city's ideal ofdiversity.
When Somerville completes the programs for the campaign, a plaque will be awarded to the city hall.
This will serve as a sign for the "entrance" to the community, and will be listed in a regional registry of
participating municipalities.
"On behalfoftheADL, Massachusetts Municipal Association, and over50 othercoalition members,
we are thrilled to have the City ofSomerville begin the processtoward being declared No Place for Hate,"
said Kelly Vest, ADL assistant director, in a press release. "Bytakingpart in thisprogram,the community
ofSomerville will be helping to set a standard ofrespect for diversity and anti-bias efforts, not only in
theircity, but in the largercommunity as well. We look forward to workingwith members ofthe Somerville
community to achieve this very "important goal."
Pictures courtesy of www.nike.com
Do you copy?
This is the first time - or, at least, the first time in a while - that
a Featuring has been written by a copy editor. And most ofyou are
probably wondering, "what is a copy editor anyway? I've never
seen this girl's name under a byline before, why is she writing?"
Okay, so I can answer the first question for you pretty easily 
a copy editor is generally the last person to read the newspaper
before it gets printed. We see the paper the way it will look in final
printand look itoverfor all gram 
matical, typographical, layout,
and othermistakes. Now, you're
eitherthinking, "wow, you have
an importantjob," or"ifyou got
stuck doing that job, they must
really not like you down there at
the Daily."
Actually, I love what I do. In high school I worked as a writing
center tutor during lunch and after school, helping other students
with their papers. I'd always been pretty good at proofreading and
enjoyed it, so workingthere was a great way to use that skill. When
I got to college, I kept up my editing by volunteering to read my
friends' papers, as long as they didn't mind the marks I would put
all over them and my chicken scratch handwriting (let's put it this
way, ;t's a good thing you're seeingthis typed). But outside ofthat,
I wasn't doing much correcting. In fact, I wasn't even doing much
writing because Ibecame aquantitative economics major (yes, I like
saying that just to scare people).
Outside ofmy major, I became involved in a variety ofextracur 
ricular activities. Like most freshmen, I putmyselfon way too many
organizations' e-mail lists and gradually picked and chose what
was important. By sophomore year I had it more planned out; I
became the president of Tufts Friends of Israel and co-chair of
Hillel's conservative committee. I worked hard with others plan 
ning programs and running religious services, but somehow I
wasn't completely happy. I loved both organizations, but I didn't
like being the one organizing the events. And part of me missed
what I did in high school and longed to get back to it.
So, aftertwo years ofinvolving myselfin all different activities
on campus, I decided to askabout something I had been wondering
for a while: "Howdo you become a copy editor forthe Daily?" I had
thought I would need to be a writer first becausethat was the policy
ofthe newspaper at my high school. Ifyou wanted to be any kind
ofeditor, you had to write first, and that didn't interest me at all.
When I finally inquired about the Daily, it turned out I didn't have
to write, so there was nothing holding me back.
I volunteered to help with the commencementissue since I knew
I'd be on campus then. The people in charge told me to come down
to Curtis Hall around 9 p.m. I think. All I rememberfor certain is that
Iwas there until 7 a.m. the next day. I think the other people working
must have thought I was crazy, because here I was, not even
officially on the Daily, and I spent the entire night there. For those
ofyou who don'tknow me, I am a night person, but even Ican admit
that 7 a.m. is a bit excessive. Even so, I had a great time, and I knew
that I had found a way to get back to what I loved doing.
At the beginning ofthis, my junior year, I decided I wanted to
work for the newspaper onaregular basis. I put in the time and the
effort, and I felt appreciated. Because of my help at key times, I
became a copy editorand I'vebeen having a greattime with it. After
my late commencement issue night, I'vetried to be around for a lot
ofthe bigger issues that run into the morning hours. Sure, most
readers outthere have no ideathat I exist, much less any about what
I do. That's okay; maybe that's why I'm writing for once.
I'm not sayingthat everyone shouldjointhe Daily(although I'm
sure someofoureditors would appreciate it),justthat it's never too
late to start something new. One ofthe coolest stories I heard was
of a man who, although he was retired and living among other
retired peers, decided to go to medical school at age 60 or SQ. He
had his residency and then practiced for ten years before being
forced to retire again. When friends asked him about it, he said
those were the best ten years ofhis life; he finally did something
he really loved.
Iheard thatstory on the radiowhile driving to work thissumm~r.
It made me think about myjob and realize that the part I liked best
about it was the proofreading. I interned for the office in charge of
mental health and substance abuse grants under the Department
of Health and Human Services, and a lot of my work, like most
internships, involved photocopying and mailing. However, my
boss let me assist her in editingthe official summary statements of
the grant applications, a task that the other interns did their best
to avoid. Forme, however, this meantputting my skill to a practical
use.
The story on the radio made me see that I was doing something
I liked. I knew I should continue to do it to be happy, and working
at the Daily has made that possible for me.
Maybe you won't find something you like at Tufts, but there's
always Boston across the river where there are a lot ofjobs and
internships available. Whether you're a freshman or a senior, you
can always start something new. So don't be afraid to try that thing
you've been meaning to do; make the time and do it. I found
something I love to do right at Tufts: copy editing.'
Karen Forseter is a Copy Editor ofthe Daily. She'llprobably read
over your next paperfor you ifyou ask her nicely. -Kelly Wisnewski
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_4" n="4" type="page">
<p>4
THE TUFTS DAILY- November 29,1999
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_5" n="5" type="page">
<p>THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999
5
Arts &amp; Entertainment
6. TheAmerican President
Anotherall-American typical romantic com-
see MOVIES, page 6
elected. When the real chiefexecutive suf 
fers a stroke he is thrust into the position
full-time. Good-natured and full ofhearty
laughs, this winner features Kevin Kline in
the title role and Sigourney Weaver as the
estranged First Lady.
4. Nixon
OnlyOliver Stone could give usaBritish Sir
Anthony Hopkins and make us believe he
is one ofthemost infamous American presi 
dents of our time. This lengthy epic por 
trays Tricky Dick as both despicable and
pitiful, a true tragic hero. Of course, the
director inserts a few ofhis always contro 
versial suppositions about the way things
might have been. But then again, isn't that
what movies are for?
5. WagtheDog
With a screenplay by David Mamet and
stars Iike Robert De Niro and Dustin Hoffinan
playing off each other, this satire reaches
absurd heights as we get a look into back
room, executive office spin-doctoring. With
an election approaching and a potential
career-ending controversy hitting the fan,
Hollywood creativity finds its way into the
White House in more ways than simply the
obvious ones.
2. Bob Roberts
This fake documentary stars Tim
Robbins as a simple folk singer who
decides to run for Senator in Pennsyl 
vania. He uses both his winning smile,
a loyal entourage, and awhole slew of
dirty politics to win the seat. Both
written and directed by Robbins, the
story is both hilarious and chilling in
its ominous predictions about the fu 
ture ofpolitics. Interestingly enough,
some of his predictions have come
true already.
the atrocious accusations thrown at the
candidates in these movies, Bradley won't
mind those pesky questions about why
New Jersey smells the way it does. It could
be worse, you know.
3. Dave
This is a fun story about a simple guy,
like you and me, who gets suckered
into playing the president because he
looks exactly like the man the people
J. TheCandidate
At once realistic and satirical, this film fea 
tures Robert Redford as a naive, young
lawyer roped into running for Senator. In
the process ofhis campaign, he learns the
sad dark truth about the way people in the
world ofpolitics really function. Itwon the
Oscar for best original screenplay in 1972
and features some of the most witty and
caustic dialogue seen in a long time.Fr~m
the director of Bad News Bears, Michael
Ritchie, how could it be bad?
uneasy melange ofcampaign prom ises and
cruel mudslinging.
With such an important position at stake
during a crucial time in ournation's history,
it would be easy to be intimidated by such
a momentous decision. It will ultimately
influence our lives in numerous very real
and permanent ways. So why not start with
something not so real and a little more
entertaining:
movies.
It's the perfect
way to get your
feet wet in the
complex the
world ofpolitics.
To make choos 
ing a few flicks a
little easier, we
here at the Arts
Department put
together a list of
the best political
films out there.
They're loaded
with treachery,
murder, sex, and
bribes: and those
are justthe docu 
mentaries! Actu 
ally, a lot of the
fun in watching
these films comes
when you try to
figure out what's
true and what's
fiction. It is
harder than you
think. Ofcourse,
it is not just the
inexperienced
politicos who
can benefit from
watching afew of
these films. They
ought to help put
things in per 
spective for
today's candi 
dates. After wit 
nessing some of
Politics in fillll eXI)!ored
The Daily's all-time top ten political movies
by ROBERTWTT
Daily Editorial Board
With former Senator and presidential
candidate Bill Bradley visiting Tufts today,
Jumbos across campus are getting psyched
for the rapidly approaching presidential
race. The first primaries arejustafew months
away, and television, radio, newspapers,
and magazines will soon be filled with an
Morissette Illellows on 'MTV
Unplugged,' recasts own illlage
Los Angeles Times-Washington Post
News Service
When Alanis Morissette first
leapt into the limelight back in
1995, the word most often associ 
ated with her work was "angry."
Thanks largely to the emotional
resonance teen-age girls found in
the vengeful intensity of "You
Oughta Know," Morissette's
breakthrough single, the singer
was hailed as a new kind offemi 
nist hero, an angry young woman
who stood as the distaff equiva 
lent to alt-rock's tortured young
men.
Never mind that many of the
songs on Jagged Little Pill, her
debut album, didn't quite .fit this
pigeonhole; as far as the pundits
were concerned, Morissette's aes 
thetic could be boiled down to
"you live, you learn/you rage, you
burn."
Morissette, however, would
not be so easily categorized.
Supposed Former Infatuation
Junkie, reJeasedjust overa year
ago, supplanted her first album's
fury with spirituality and self 
reflection. Now, MTV Un 
pluggedgoes a step further and
recasts the wrath ofthose early
songs as wisdom and transcen 
dence.
Not fornothing does the album
open with the low-key jauntiness
of"You Learn." As her band eases
into an almost jazzy shuffle,
Morissette advises, "I recommend
getting your heart trampled on/To
anyone."
Where once the lyricseem~:d
infused with the bitterness ofhard 
won experience Morissette now
presents the song as a saga of
goodness and growth. It's almost
as ifshe believesthattheonly way
we can become better is by occa 
sionally doing stupid things, and
that she who dares most, gains
most.
Or, to quote the second verse:
"I recommend biting off more
than you can chew/To anyone."
MTV Unplugged itself doesn't
find Morissette biting offmuch
in the way ofnew material. Al 
though three of the album's
dozen titles are making their first
appearance on CD, none are ex 
actly new. The moody, discur 
sive "No Pressure Over
Cappuccino" made its first ap 
pearance in Morissette's reper 
toire during the Jagged tour,
while "Princes Familiar" and
"These R the Thoughts" were
written for (though not included
on) Infatuation Junkie.
Then again, this album seems
less about breaking new ground
than shattering old stereotypes.
After a year on the road, touring
behind the Infatuation Junkie al 
bum, Morissette has settled into a
comfortable, confident groove,
offering a stage presence as pow 
erful as on her first tour, yet oper 
ating on an entirely different wave 
length.
Nowhere is this more evident
than on the hits. "Ironic," reset in
an easy, mostly acoustic arrange 
ment that emphasizes not the mo 
mentum of the melody but the
space between notes, has become
a cosmic joke that has even
Morissette chuckling to 'herself,
while "Head Over Feet" under 
cuts its own self importance with
a delightfully incompetent har 
monica solo.
Even the most serious songs
have been given a new take. Al 
though "You Oughta Know" is
still shot-through with rage and
see ALANIS, page 6
'Beau Jest' to be performed at
Hillel this weekend
Thisweekend, the HillelTheaterTroupewillbemakingacomeback
after a two year hiatus with the hit comedy Beau Jest. This fun and
hysterical play by James Shennan tells the tale of how far one
characterwill go to make her parents happy. The play examines the
timeless problems thatarise whenone seeks true love while trying to
satisfy family atthe same time.
The comedy,directedby seniors Brian SchneiderandDaraResnik,
is a riotous comedy about a young Jewish woman, Sarah Goldman,
who is deeply in love with her boyfriend, Chris. There is one small
problem though. Chris is not Jewish, andSarah, who intendstomarry
him, realizes thatthis fact could causehavoc in herfamily.Shedecides
to hire an unsuspecting actor to play her beau in order to keep her
parents placated. The story proceeds with the actor's comical at 
tempts to portray a Jewish doctor. His knowledge ofJudaism, how 
ever,isabitlimited.HebaseshismedicalskiIlsonepisodesofERand
his knowledge ofJewish cultureonhis familiarity with theend-all,be~
all ofJewishmusicals, FiddlerontheRoo!Onecanonlyimagine the
craziness that ensues from this bizarre situation!
The second act, ofcourse, keeps the laughs rolling. The cast of
Beau Jest features a diverse group ofactors who are all new to the
Tufts stage, but have a great deal ofpast experience in theater. The
comedy will star senior Alan Silver, junior Matthew Waterson,
sophomore Rebecca Cohen-Shrage, and freshmen Melissa Holman,
Lara Saipe, and Evan Weinberg.
DirectorBrian Schneiderfeels the showwill appealto those ofany
faith, as the difficultthemes ofinterfaith relationships anddomineer 
ing parents are explored with lightheartedness and intelligentcom~
mentary. "Everyone can relate to this show," says Schneider, "as
we'vealltriedto impress ourparentsatonetime oranother." He adds
thatthe play'shumoris "extremelycleverandreallymakesyoulaugh
throughout the show." .
Performancesare thisSaturday, Dec. 4that8PMandSunday, Dec.
5that7PMatthe GranoffFamilyHillelCenteroncampus. Ticketsare
$5 each andare availableatthe Hillel officeorby calling 627&#183;3242.
-byAlison Damast
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_6" n="6" type="page">
<p>6
THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999
&#8226;
Child Care - Two Afternoons
GRAND OPENING DEC. IO!
I
with a cover of the old Police
song, "King of Pain." Perhaps
because she herself has been
portrayed as a Queen of Pain,
Morissette sees through to the
self-mockery at the song's core
and presents it with wry humor
that respects the melody while
asking us to think about the lyr 
ics.
It's entirely typical of what
Morissette does on her MTV Un 
pluggedand one more reason for us
to reconsideroursense ofthe singer.
continued from page 5
revenge, Morissette doesn't
burn so much as smolder, switch 
ing the focus from the
protagonist's feelings to the
misdeeds ofher former lover. By
scaling the arrangement down
and pulling the energy back,
Morissette lets us hear the song,
not the fury, and that makes a
world ofdifference.
Ofcourse,_ it doesn't hurt that
she prefaces "YouOughta Know"
Alanis shatters stereotypes
with new Unplugged album
ALANIS
. -
_.
CAUFORNIA
EARN UP TO $600IMONTH
CRYeBANK.INC.
REPRODUC11VE TISSUE SEIllCES The Cambridge office of Califqrnia Cry-
obank, Inc, is seeking heallhy males
between the ages of 19 and 39 to participate in our anonymous sperm
donation program. To qualify, you must be 5'9" or taller, enrolled in or
graduated from a 4-year COllege/university, and be able 10 commit for 9-
12 months. Donors are compensated $50.00 for each acceptable dona-
tion provided. Hours: 8:00AM to 6:00PM Monday-Friday. Call California
Cryobank, Inc. at (617)-497-864610 see if YOU qualify!
newly elected Senator arrives to
take his seat and is immediately
overwhelmed by dirty politicians
itching to capture his idealism and
take advantage of it before he
knows what hit him. He stands his
ground, though, and fights the
mob simply to do the right thing.
10. President Clinton's Testi 
mony for Kenneth Star'sSpecial
Investigation
Sure to go down in history as a sad
day for democracy and the White
House. This one provides hours
offun on a rainy day. Slick Willy
. comes clean discussing his rela 
tionships with all kinds ofpeople.
Some ofthosepeoplecare for him.
Others work for him. Some are kind.
Some are cunning. Someare loyal.
And some just suck.
8. All the President's Men
For all ofthose aspiring investi 
gative reporters out there, this
one is for you. It is the story of
Washington Post reporters Bob
Woodward (Robert Redford) and
Carl Bernstein (Dustin Hoffman)
taking on the Watergate scandal
with little support and few leads.
They end up, however, breaking
the story wide open. Watch for
those eerie parking garage
scenes with the mysterious Deep
Throat.
9. Mr.Smith GoesToWashington
Foreveryone outthere who thinks
that our government is corrupt
and wishes they could go to D.C.
and change a few things, Jimmy
Stewart is the man for you. In this
classic, directed by Frank Capra, a
Bradley's visit prompts our top ten list
MOVIES
continued from page 5
edy, we are given Michael Dou 
glas as a widowed president
searching for love while holding
the nation's highest office. Typi 
cal fare from director Rob Reiner,
this one tries to pull on our
heartstrings and succeeds.
Call Marianne
(617) 345&#183;7003 (days) and (781) 721-1621 (evenings and weekends).
Ifyou cannot do the 12:00 school transfer, please call anyway.
We are looking for child care on Wednesday anclJor Friday afternoons. We live in
Winchester, and the duties would be to drive our 5 year old from a school in Medford
(Eliot Pearson) to a school in Winchester (Lynch) at noon and then pick him up and
bring him home at 2:45. At home at that time would be our 10 and 13 year old daughters.
There may be some driving to afternoon activities. We get home from work at
6:00 p.m. We are offering $75 per day. Must have own car. References required.
Special Egg Donor Needed
$25,000
We are a loving, infertile couple hoping to find a compassionate woman to help us
hft\"e a baby. We're looking for a healthy, intelligent college student or college
graduate, age 21-33, with blue eyes and blonde or light brown hair. Compensation
$25,000 plus expenses. Your gift of life would bring great jO)'. Please contact us
through our representative at 1-800-776-7680./"'-~;:;'h('f&lt;'~"fl&gt;"
:Glr'i""~\'I)
\ y/,J. (
\-C:~~~:~7
7. All the King's Men
An old one but still a great one.
Basedonthenovel by Robert Penn
Warren, it tells the story of the
tragic rise and fall of Southern
governor Willie Stark and his
lackey, Jack Burden. The novel is
itselfbased loosely on the story of
demagogue and Louisana Gover 
nor Huey Long. It was made in
1949 but still fares well today. A
classic.
Now You Only
~dveTo Borrow
~dlfAsMu(~
Money from
Your Roommdte.
Monday nights from 10 'til dose. flash us your college 1.0.
and all appetizers are just half price.
33 Dunster Street Harvard Square (617)868-3585
'S
Don.'t: Iniss our Grand
Opening Specials!
Broadways's newest full service restaurant/bar and billiard
club! Did we also mention our lO-foot giant TV for all your
favorite sporting events? A contemporary atmosphere for
all your entertainment needs.
No""," hiring~orall positions.
Stop by or caJ.I (617) 629-5302.
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_7" n="7" type="page">
<p>THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999
Sports
7
see BASKETBALL, page 11
after Tufts' season openeragainst
RPI. The gamewas tightthe whole
way, and the Jumbos held the lead
heading into the final minutes of
the game. RPI was able to puta run
together and overtake the Jum 
bos, however, and cameaway with
a 75-69 victory. .
"Itwasaclose, back-and-forth
game the whole way," Sheldon
said. "We were ahead with about
five orsix minutes left. They were
17-8 last yearwith only one senior,
though, and their experience just
came through in the end."
Tufts led 42-37 atthe halfafter
shooting a red-hot 63.2 percent in
the opening period, but turnovers
plagued the team throughout the
game and the Jumbos could not
hold on to their lead. With junior
co-captain Bobby Mpuku out, and
Andrews and Flaherty, who fin 
ished with 14 points despite lim 
ited playing time, in foul trouble,
the team lacked the on-court lead 
ership and experience it needed to
take careoftheball. The result was
a disappointing 28 turnovers, a
setback the team could not over 
come.
"Thewhole story [against RPI]
was turnovers," Sheldon said.
"Nottomakean excuse, but Bobby
Mpuku didn't play. We'd been
building up for two and a half
weeks to have him play at the
point, and Mike [Andrews] just
started practicing [at point guard]
Monday. We kind ofdid it point
guard by committee, and it was
tough for us to get in the flow of
stuff. There's nothing that could
have hurt us more than missing
our point guard the first game."
however. NYU forward Brian
Beggans had six points down the
stretch to help his team hold on to
its lead, and graduate student Mike
Andrews' field goal with five sec 
onds remaining could only cut itto
66-63. That was as close as the
Jumboswould get, as all NYU had
to do was let the clock tick down.
Despite the loss, the Jumbos
came away from the game with a
number ofpositives. The biggest
was the playofFlaherty, whodomi 
nated in the paint, scoring 30 and
grabbing 17 rebounds while play 
ing all but one minute ofthe game.
He also demonstrated his ability
away from the basket, sinking two
offourthree-pointattempts, while
going4-5 from the free throw line.
"[Flaherty] had a great game,"
Sheldon said. "He's our number
one option and they realized it.
We're going to go to him, and I
think he's going to have a great
year."
Andrews also stepped up his
play, settling into the point guard
position to put up 11 points and
five assists to just two turnovers.
As a whole, Tufts was able to cut
down significantly on turnovers
in the second half, only giving up
the ball four times. The Jumbos
edged out their opponents on the
boards, holding a 38-36 advan 
tage in rebounds, and shot 47 per 
cent compared to NYU's4l.
"We didn't want to have to
play NYU in the first game on
Sunday, but we had to," Sheldon
said. "We playedagoodgame, we
out-rebounded them, and we shot
better from the field. They're a
pretty good team, too, and we did
everythingandjustcameup short."
The loss came just one day
Photo by Daniel Rodrigues
Graduate student Mike Andrews filled in at point guard for
Tufts, contributing 20 points and eight assists in two games.
Men's
Basketball
Men's Basketball Statistics
Record: 0-2
Name
FG ATT FG% FT FTA FT% REB AST PTS
PPG
Dan Flaherty
17 29 58.6 6 9 66.7 19 I 44 22.0
Paul Smith
II 17 64.7 4 6 66.7 8 5 28
14.0
Mike Andrews
7 II 63.6 5 7 71.4 6 8 20 10.0
Bobby McMannis
4 10 40.0 2 3 66.7 3 4 14
7.0
Fred Pedroletti
4 12 33.3 4 6 66.7 II 3 12
6.0
Eddie Vazquez
0 0 0.0 2 3 66.7 0 0 2
2.0
Kyle Van Natta
I 6 16.7 0 0 0.0 5 I 3
1.5
Tom Bernier
I I 100.0 0 0 0.0 5 I 2 1.0
Lee Neugebauer
I 4 25.0 0 I 0.0 3 0 2 1.0
Brandon McKenzie
I I 100.0 0 0 0.0 2 0 2 1.0
Brian Shapiro
0 2
. 0.0
0 0 0.0 I 0 2 1.0
Bruce Reese
0 I 0.0 I 2 50.0 I I I 0.5
Monday, November29
No Games Scheduled
UPCOMING SCHEDULE
nament on Nov. 20 and 21. Tufts
suffered two close losses to open
the season, falling to RPI and NYU
by scores of75-69 and 66-63, re 
spectively. The Jumbos are not
too worried about the slow start,
however, since they have over 
come a number of obstacles and
are already starting to show signs
ofimprovement.
"We're 0-2, but we weren't at
full strength, and we played two
good teams," coach Bob Sheldon
said. "To play them both down to
the last shotthe way we did Ithink
says a lot for where we're going
this year. It'sjust a matter ofget 
ting everybody healthy and get 
ting back."
Tufts faced off against host
NYU in the consolation game on
Sunday,Nov. 20after losingto RPI
the day before. Even though Tufts
put together an all-around solid
game, the team was unable to keep
up with its opponent, gradually
falling farther and farther behind.
Nor did the Jumbos help them 
selves, committing 13 turnovers in
the first period. By the half, NYU
had built up a solid nine-point
lead, despite shootingjust 35 per 
cent from the floor.
The lead grew to as much as 16
in the second halfbefore the Jum 
bos began to mount a comeback.
Tufts slowly battled.its way back
into the game, withjuniorco-cap 
tain Dan Flaherty leading the way.
Flaherty scored 13 points in the
final ten minutes, and the Jumbos
cut the margin down to four with
4: 17 left on the clock. The team
could not overcome the deficit,
Tuesday, November30
Men's Basketball: @ Suffolk,
7:30 p.m.
Women's Basketball: vs.
Babson, 7 p.m.
Women's Squash: @
Wellesley, 7 p.m.
JUlDbos drop two close gaines
at NYU Invitational Tourney
Tufts fulls victim to turnovers without starting point guard
by BEN OSHLAG
Daily Editorial Board
Themen'sbasketball team took
a small step in the wrong direction
duringthe NYU Invitational Tour-
Inside a rivalry
Jon Japha
My Thanksgiving break took me home to Colorado, and I was
fortunate to land a ticket to the best game in town. Every Friday after
Thanksgiving the Colorado Buffaloes play the NebraskaCornhuskers.
In past years, this game has meantatriptothe Orange Bowl and ashot
at a National Championship, but, more than anything, this game is
about pride.
For Nebraska, a team that is almost always
in the National Championship hunt, beating Colo 
rado has become second nature, but it still views the
post-Thanksgiving game with a little more passion
than its games with other strong Big 12 teams.
Yeah, this rivalry used to be important back
in the late 80s and early 90s, when Colorado was a
perennial national powerhouse and Nebraska, un 
der coach Tom Osborne, was still searching for a
Bowl victory. In fact, the joke in
Ie II
Colorado went: Why does Tom
Mile High Osborne eat cereal off of a plate?
'=========="""'" Because he can't reach a bowl.
Nowthosejokesdon'thave the sameeffect withNebraskawinning
three National Championships in the past five years. Nebraska has
won the past eight matchups in a rivalry that used to be grouped
among the best in the country. For Nebraska, it'sjust another impor 
tant game and nothing more.
That is not the case at all in Colorado. For the Buffaloes, this game
is the season. They could go0-1 0, beatthe Huskers, and go outhappy.
Hatred towards Nebraska is taught to Colorado youth from birth. I
know nothing morethan to hate anyone with a Nebraska license plate.
If you're born in Colorado, you can't look at red - Nebraska's
obnoxious color-withoutthinking aboutthe programthat Nebraska
has built. Of course, we think about the negative aspects of the
program - the Lawrence Phillips and the Christian Peters, who
assaulted and battered their way through school. We ignore the eight
straight beatings and the three National Championships.
All we know is that Nebraska players are criminals, their coach is
a deity in the state, and the rabid fans are hicks and rednecks and
farmers who have nothing better to do than drive eight hours on a
Saturday to watch their beloved Huskers play, even though most of
them couldn'thave graduated from third grade. This isjustwhatwe're
taught.. .. I don't really think it's the truth.... Maybe.
For one insane week you cannot wear red in Boulder. When one
Colorado assistant coach wore a red plaid sh irt to practice, his players
tore it offand continued practice with a shirtless coach. The town is
plastered Black and Gold and "Huck the Fuskers" signs are ubiqui 
tous.
Personally, Icouldn'twaitto see a big-time college game. Through 
out the game, I kept drawing comparisons to Tufts' football games,
and none were favorable. The atmosphere in Boulder was electric.
Kids and adults, both donning Black and Gold face paint, surrounded
us in the 52,000-seat stadium.
OneofColorado's mascots is a real buffalo, which runs around the
field atthebeginningofeach half. Forthe first time in as long as anyone
can remember, though, it refused to run. This was an inauspicious start
for the Buffs, who were 14- 1/2 point underdogs and showed itthrough
the first three quarters, trailing 27-3 enteringthe fourth. Whatamazed
me was that not only had no one left, we hadn't even sat down the
entire game! At Tufts, if the Jumbos are in the midst ofa blowout,
students head back to their dorm rooms and then sit down.
It was as ifeight years worth ofexperience had told the fans that
this game was far from over. It didn't matter that the Buffs were
unranked and getting manhandled by the number three team in the
country, the fans remained standing. The 45-year-old engineering
student in front ofus kept drinking heavily out ofhis cooler, and y,elled
a variation ofthe"Huckthe Fuskers" sign. His prayers were answered,
as the Buffs hucked the fuskers into atie score, at 27-27, and had a34 
yard field goal with one second left in regulation to win.
We were all planningthe bestroute onto the field. CU's kicker had
already made a 49-yarder, and there was no question he was putting
this onethrough. We were ready to chargethe field, teardown the goal
posts, pass them upthe stadium, and throw them over. Sure, it'sa little
dangerous, but when you haven't beaten a team in eight years, a few
lives can be sacrificed for the sake ofmob violence.
These grand schemes never materialized, though, as the wind, or
some ungodly presence, pushed the ball wide right. I'm pretty sure the
old engineering student in front of us started to cry, and I couldn't
blame him. He had put his heart and soul and liver on the line for the
game, and came up empty.
AfterCU lostthe game in overtime, an amazing thing happened. No
one left the stadium. Both the players and the fans were in shock, and
no one could move. The undulating emotions had taken its toll on
everyone in Boulder. The Buffs had gone from a 24-point deficit to a
chanceto win the game, and now it was overbefore anyone was ready.
So what's the point ofthis little narrative? I think it's to show that
it doesn't matter what level offootball your school is playing, ifyour
team is in a big game, you should be there the whole time, standing,
cheering, crying when they lose, chargingthe field when they win, and
drinking heavily out ofa coolerthe whole way. Sure, Tufts could use
a legitimate rival, but why don't we support our teams fully every
week?
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_8" n="8" type="page">
<p>Off the Hill
THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999
NEWS Editors:
Benjamin Gedan, Will Kinlaw, Brooke Menschel
Jeremy Wang-Iverson
Assistant Editors:
Jordan Solomon, Ilene Stein
Production Managers:
Sandra Fried, Cindy Marks, Valentina Clark
LAYOUT Assistant Editor:
Jenny Ahn
COPY Editors:
'Cambra Stern, Ruthie Nussbaum, Reshma Bharne
Jonathan Dworkin, Phil Erner, Karen Forseter
Michael Dupuy
Production Director
PRODUCTION
SPORTS Editors:
Ben Oshlag, Russell Capone, Jon Japha
Assistant Editor:
Adam Kamins
ARTS Editors:
Dara Resnik, Alison Damast, Adam Machanic, Rob Lott
FEATURES Editors:
Kim Fox, Kelly Wisnewski
Assistant Editors:
Lesley Bogdanow, Sheryl Gordon
VIEWPOINTS Editor:
Dave Steinberg
Assistant Editors:
Leigh Wald
DanielBarbarisi,
David J. Ball
Associate Editors
Jordan Brenner
Managing Editor
Lauren M. Heist
Editor-in-Chief
EDITORIAL
ONLINE Editor:
Jeff Carlon, Sonal Mukhi
PHOTOGRAPHY Editors:
Kate Cohen, Eric Anderson, Daniel Rodrigues
THE TUFTS DAILyG&gt;
8
Religion thriving on campuses across US
BUSINESS
Stephanie Wagner
Executive Business Director
Business Manager: Stephanie Adaniel
Office Manager: Laura Giuliano
Advertising Managers: Pamela Abrams, Grace Lee
Receivables Manager: Michelle Herman
EDITORIAL POLICY
The Tufts Daily is a non-profit, independent newspaper, published
Monday through Friday during the academic year, and distributed free
to the Tufts community. Business hours are 9 a.m. - 6 p.m., Monday
through Friday, 1 - 6 p.m. on Sunday. The Daily is printed at Charles
River Publishing, Charlestown, MA.
Editorials appear on this page, unsigned. Individual editors are not
necessarily responsible for, or in agreement with, the policies and
editorials of The Tufts Daily. The content of Letters, advertisements,
signed columns, cartoons, and graphics does not necessarily reflect the
opinion of The Tufts Daily editorial board.
Advertising deadlines: all display ads are to be submitted to The
Tufts Daily office by 3:00 p.m. two business days before the ad is to run.
Deadlines are not negotiable. Late ads will run only at the discretion
of the Advertising Manager and may be subjected to a late fee. All
advertising copy is subject to the approval of the Editor-in-Chief,
Executive Board, and Executive Business Director. A publication
schedule and rate card are available upon request.
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Letters must be submitted by 4 p.m. and should be handed into the
Daily office or sent to tdaily@emerald.tufts.edu. All Letters must be
word processed and include the writer's name and phone number.
There is a 350-word limit and Letters must be verified by the Daily.The
editors reserve the right to edit Letters for clarity, space, and length. For
the full policy on Letters to the Editor, contact The Tufts Daily.
TMS Campus News Service
CHICAGO - Religion is thriving on col 
lege campuses, but it doesn't look much like
the high-church services students' parents
may have attended years ago.
Students these days are more into spiritual
exploration than formal worship, researchers
behind a new study funded by the Lilly En 
dowment report. They presented their find 
ings this week at the annual conference ofthe
American Academy ofReligion.
The study focused on four campuses that
were not identified but chosen for their dis 
tinct character. They were a state university
enrolling more than 30,000 students, a Lutheran
liberal-arts college with about 3,000 students,
a private, historically black university with
fewer than 1,500 students, and a Roman Catho 
lic university with more than 8,000 students.
Researchers studied each campus for two
years. They talked with hundreds of students
and professors and observed religion classes
and worship services.
Despite each campus' distinct religious
character, researchers said students shared
some common traits:
. They were more likely to consider them 
selves "spiritual" than "religious." Students
viewed spirituality as a continuing journey
and religion as a fixed set ofrules handed down
from their ancestors, said Conrad Cherry, di 
rector ofthe Center for the Study ofReligion
and American Culture at Indiana University 
Purdue University Indianapolis, who led the
project.
&#183; They were not likely to participate in reli 
gious organizations or attend worship ser 
vice, but they didn't think that was an accurate
indicator oftheir interest in religion.
&#183; They were very interested in courses on
religion and deemed them a useful means by
which they could sort out their own beliefs.
&#183; They felt spirituality and social service were
closely linked. And while they may have their
own, unique approach to religion, they still
considered public service an expression of
their religious beliefs.
With the exception of the state university
- where no one religion appeared to dominate
- each of the campuses studied had its own
religious identity, researchers said. They also
noted that the campuses appeared to enjoy a
significant amount ofreligious tolerance - an
indication, researchers said, that students
aren't as loyal as their parents to anyone
denomination.
The study did reveal some tensions. Evan 
gelical Christian groups were perceived by
many to be anti-intellectual and superficial.
Some professors also reported that they had a
hard time persuading evangelical Christians
ofthe importance ofbetter understanding non 
Western religions. Researchers said they also
found discord among religion professors, some
of whom viewed themselves as teachers of
religious history, and others ofwho felt they
should contribute to a student's spiritual
growth.
http://www.tuftsdaily.com
The Tufts Daily
P.O. Box 53018
Medford MA 02153
Telephone: (617) 627-3090
FAX: (617) 627-3910
E-mail: tdaily@emerald.tufts.edu
LBttBt!: to thB~ditOtWBICOfnB:
tdaily@ BtnBtald.tuft!:.Bdu
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_9" n="9" type="page">
<p>THE TUFTS DAILY- November 29, 1999
9
National/WorId News
Ulster Unionists back deal for shared governntent
Russian bontbardtnent kills hund'reds
Taliban greets UN sanctions with defiance
"This is the lesser of
two evils and we've got
to give it a try."
- Tom Davison
Delegate from Bangor
the days collectingfirewood to bumfor warmth,
the traditional Afghan welcome for bin Laden,
a once-revered Muslim guest, seems to be
wearingth in.
"It is our custom to be hospitable to guests,
but we would also like Osamato leave because
ofall the innocent people," said Mohammad
Taj, 45, a laborer waiting in line for his daily
see UNIONISTS, page 11
interview from Grozny broadcast
on the independentNTV network.
"We wish the Russians would
launch a(ground)assau It. We want
closer contact with them."
The new wave ofbombing has
increased the flow ofrefugees out
of Chechnya. Russian officials
reported thatnearly 2,000 people
arrived in the last two days at
refugee camps in the neighboring
republic of Ingushetia. An esti 
mated220,000 had fled earlier. Itis
not known how many Chechen
civilians remain inside the repub 
lic, including in Grozny.
The Russian military campaign
began eight weeks ago after the
rebels led two incursions into the
neighboring republic ofDagestan
and after a series of apartment
bombings in Moscow and else 
where killed nearly 300 people.
Russian leaders say they have
traced the bombers to Chechnya,
but have provided no evidence to
support the claim.
Western leaders have harshly
condemned the Russian cam 
paign, sayingthe size and strength
ofthe attacksare outofproportion
to the danger posed by the terror 
ists Moscow says it is fighting.
On Saturday, outgoing IMF
Director Michel Camdessus
warned that the West is unwilling
tofinance the wareitherdirectly or
indirectly and may decide to cut
offaid ifthe fighting continues.
Russians overwhelmingly sup 
port the war.
But the Russian army's image
has suffered in recentdays follow 
ing an incident at a refugee camp
in Ingushetia on Thursday in
which a groupofdrunken Russian
soldiers opened fire on sales 
woman who said she had no liquor
for sale at her kiosk. The woman
was killed and two other people
were injured. Five soldiers were
arrested Friday and confessed to
the killing on Saturday, Russian
news reports said.
Inan effortto containthe crisis,
which has been widely covered in
the Russian media, Defense Min 
ister Igor D. Sergeyev senta letter
of apology to Ingush President
Ruslan Aushev.
step compromise was entirely in
the hands ofthe Ulster Unionist
council, and Trimble was by no
means guaranteed their support
going into the closed-door meet 
ing in Belfast on Saturday morn 
ing.
Six ofthe ten Unionist mem 
bers ofthe British Parliament al 
ready had declared their opposi 
tion to the deal. The council,
made up ofindependent-minded
farmers, homemakers, smaIl-busi 
ness owners, and local politi 
cians, was seen as highly unpre 
dictable.
Trimble called the meeting at
the modern Waterfront Hall, on
the banks ofthe Lagan River.
According to delegates, the
three-hourdebate was highly emo 
tional, with 27 people speakingfor
oragainstthe motion that Trimble
put forward to allow him to pro 
ceed until February.
The final vote was 480-349,
about 58 percent in Trimble's fa 
vor. It was short ofthe two-thirds
human rights groups say increase
the number ofcivilian casualties.
Russian officials have consistently
discounted such reports, saying
thattheirweaponshave"pinpoint"
accuracy and that many of the
civilians killed were beingused by
the rebels as "human shields."
Chechen guerrillas inflicted
serious losses on the Russian army
during street battles in the last war,
and Russian officers are clearly
reluctant to engage in any form of
close combat. To date, their strat 
egy has been to shell the rebels
from a distance until they retreat.
"I think a dramatic change in
hostilities will occur in the near
future," Chechen Security Minis 
ter Turpal Atgeriyev said in an
ofbloody conflict. But after days
of intense talks with the British
and Irish prime ministers in July,
Trimble refused, and the so-called
Good Friday peace agreement ap 
peared on the
verge of col 
lapse.
Mitchell,
the former US
Senatem~or&#173;
ity leaderwho
had brokered
the original
agreement, was called back in Sep 
tember. Under the deal he ham 
mered out with the two sides,
Trimble agreed to form a govern 
ment with Sinn Fein in exchange
for a public commitment by the
IRA to nameaseniormembertoan
international commission on dis 
armament.
The IRA representative would
be appointed on the same day the
cabinet took power, and disarma 
mentwould be completed by May
2000, according to the termsofthe
Good Friday accord.
But the fate of the step-by-
see AFGHANISTAN, page 11
month as a night watchman. "This is the time
they should be helping us, but instead they are
aiming these cruel actions against us because
ofone man."
Bin Laden, an Islamic extremist who has
reportedly maintained a base in Afghanistan
for several years, is believed by US officials in
Washington to have planned and financed the
bombings oftwo US embassies in East Africa
in August 1998, in which 224 peopledied. Later
that month, the United States launched a cruise 
missile attack against Afghan training camps
allegedly under his control.
Sincethen, Taliban officials have offeredto
prosecute or monitor bin Laden, but they have
refused all US demands to tum him overfor trial
in the United States. In retaliation, Washington
banned all US trade and investment with Af 
ghanistan, and in October the UN Security
Council threatened further sanctions if the
regime did not comply. When it did not, the
sanctions took effect.
Although the sanctions do not prohibit
food imports, medical relief, ortrade between
Afghanistan and its customary partners in
nearby Muslim countries, the sanctions have
come at a timeofmultiple new hardships here.
A drought caused a poor wheat harvest this
fall, Pakistan's new military government has
cracked down on unregulated trade and winter
has struck this war-scarred, largely heatless
capital with unexpected ferocity.
In addition, the new sanctions have made it
more complicated for Afghans to receive cash
ing pauses in the bombing, resi 
dents scurry into the street to col 
lect water from puddles.
"Grozny does not have a single
hospital or medical clinic,"
Dudayev said, according to
Interfax. "Ifpassersby don'tcarry
the wounded to a clinic outside of
town, they just die on the spot."
Russian officials describe the
two-day-old assault on Grozny as
the decisivephase in theircampaign
to rid the country of"bandits and
terrorists" and regain control ofthe
separatist republic, which wrested
itselffrom Russian rule in 1996 after
a 21-month war for independence.
Russian forces are shelling the
city from the airand with powerful,
long-range artillery weapons that
that the peace process will work,
although many are willing togive
it a try.
Northern Ireland's pro-British
Unionists - the vast majority of
whom are Prot-
estants
along with the
Catholic minor 
ity that wants to
be united with
the Republic of
Ireland, signed
a peace agree-
ment in April 1998 calling for the
establishment ofa regional gov 
ernment with Sinn Fein in ex 
change for the disarmament of
paramilitary groups such as the
IRA.
The accord was overwhelm 
ingly endorsed by Protestant and
Catholic voters, butuntil now nei 
ther side had been willing to take
the first step.
The British, Irish, and US gov 
ernments had all pressed Trimble
to abandon his "no guns, no gov 
ernment" policy and test Sinn
Fein'scommitmenttoend 30 years
"Every few'years the United
States looks forsomeone
new to hate. Before it was
Libya and Iraq, now it is
Afghanistan's turn."
- Wakil Ahmad Muttawakil,
Foreign Minister of the Taliban
regime
bread ration. "The people with powerwill sup 
port themselves, and the sanctions will only
hurtthepoor. Americashould havemoremercy,
but the mullahs must solve this problem with
the United Nations, too."
Many Afghan people blame the United
States and its allies for imposing new economic
hardships on them. A week ago, buildings
occupiedbyUN employees in six Afghan cities
were stoned or burned by mobs, even though
they provide the bulk offood and medical aid
to the country.
"We are a weak country now, and America
is trying to keep us that way," said Abdul
Razaq, 30, a father of five who earns $4 per
Los Angeles Times-Washington
Times News Service
MOSCOW - Russia intensi 
fied its bombardment ofthe rebel
capital ofGroznyon Saturday, un 
leashing wave after waveofrocket
and bomb attacks that local offi 
cials said left hundreds ofcivilians
dead.
Residents have so farreport,~d
260 deaths since the new Russian
assault on the Chechen capital
begantwodaysago,GroznyMayor
Lecha Dudayev told the IntertiX
news agency. He said he expects
the fmal tally to be twice as large.
The intensity ofthe attack is so
great that residents sheltering in
basements are no longer safe, he
added. The city has no food. Dur-
to you. We'vejumped. Youfol 
low."
Adams said Trimble's ultima 
tum went beyond the terms of
the compromise painstakingly
crafted during five weeks ofne 
gotiations with US mediator
George Mitchell.
"Itis, in my opinion, the wrong
way to sort this matter out,"
Adams told British Broadcasting
Corp. radio. "Itwill fuel the uncer 
tainty and it will also keep alive
the hope of the rejectionists (of
the peace process) inside and
outside the Ulster Unionist
Party."
Many Unionists do notbelieve
thatthe IRA intends to getrid onts
weapons at all, and they see the
agreement as a con by the repub 
licans to get intogovernmentwhile
keeping a private army toenfon~e
theirwill.
Others suggest that Sinn Fein
might be sincere about trading
bullets for democratic politics, but
does not have the clout to con 
vince the IRA to disarm. Few
Unionists say they areconvincc~d
Los Angeles Times-Washington Times News
Service
KABUL, Afghanistan- In the chilly corri 
dorsofpower, Taliban officialshuddled around
space heaters are as defiant as ever about the
cause ofOsama bin Laden, the wealthy Saudi
fugitive whose alleged terrorist attacks and
continued sanctuary in Afghanistan have led
to new UN economic sanctions against the
impoverished nation.
"The United States wants us to tie Osama
bin Laden's hands and send him to them as a
gift," said Wakil Ahmad &#165;uttawakil, the new
foreign ministeroftheTaIiban regime. "Weare
ready to talk on all issues. We have offered to
have him tried here, or to have other Muslim
countriesjudgehim. Buthow can we givethem
a human being as a gift, especially ifhis crime
has not been provenT'
Muttawakil said Saturday in an interview
that he expects only minor long-term impact
from the UN sanctions, which have grounded
all foreign flights by Afghanistan's only airline
and frozen Taliban assets abroad since they
tookeffectNov. 14. He declared that Allah will
protect the Afghan people from hardship at
foreign hands.
"Every few yearsthe United States looks for
someone new to hate. Before it was Libya and
Iraq, now it is Afghanistan's tum," he said.
"But if they try to harm us, they will gain
nothing. Almighty God always accepts the
prayers ofthe innocentand defends those who
are trampled upon."
But on the frozen streets of the capital,
where families shiver in bread lines or spend
Los Angeles Times-Washington Post
News Service
BELFAST,Northern Ireland 
Overcoming decadesofhatredand
deep internal divisions, Northern
Ireland's largest Protestantpoliti 
cal party decided Saturdayto back
a compromise deal to set up a
power-sharing government with
Roman Catholics before the Irish
Republican Army begins to dis 
arm.
The Ulster Unionist Party
council's vote clears the way for
Northern Ireland to establish its
frrstprovincial governmentin more
than a quarter century.
Parties in the Northern Ireland
Assembly are expected to name a
12-member cabinet on Monday
that would assume powers from
the British governmentbefore the
end ofthe week.
The Ulster Unionist council's
vote is a triumph for party chief
David Trimble, who is to become
first minister ofthe new provin 
cial government. Trimble forged
the compromise with Gerry
Adams, leader ofthe IRA's po 
litical wing, Sinn Fein, and then
put his own leadership on the
line seekingthe supportofUnion 
ists.
To do so, Trimble effectively
gave Sinn Fein a deadline oftwo
to three months top~rsuadethe
IRA to begin getting rid of its
weapons. He promised the 858 
member council a chance to vote
on the deal again in February and
told them that ifthe IRA had not
started disarming by then, he
wouldresign as first ministerand
pull the party out ofthe govern 
ment.
Trimblewonthe vote andthrew
down the gauntlet to the leader of
Sinn Fein.
"This clears the stalemate we
have had in terms of the pro 
cess," Trimble said. "Now, we've
done ourbit. Mr. Adams, it's over
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_10" n="10" type="page">
<p>10
, '
. .... _. ... . ..
THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999
-,
Bill Nave
kids from drowning, but he's
not a lifegui1rd.
Verleeta Wooten found
several new stars, but&#183;
she's n()t an astrc)nomer.
And Ivan Neal/Jut out
a lot offires, but he's
not a firefighter.
These are teachers ..But to the
kids they reach, they're heroes.
BE A TEACHER. BE A HERO.
Call1-800-'45-TEACH.
,r!1. A Public Service 01
ua . This Publication
lDlOCI
I'hoto,~:Ho/J;n \&lt;Ichs
Reach for the Power
TEACH
RlCRUmNG NEWnACN~IlS.INC,
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_11" n="11" type="page">
<p>THE TUFTS DAILY&#183; November 29, 1999 11
EVENTS
Freshman Female Englneersl
Get help choosing a major! Join SWE
on Nov. 30th at 7pm to in the large
conference room in thecampuscenter
to discuss classes, majors, intemships
etc. Free dinner will be served!
Make Some Plans Before Going
Abroad
All Student who are not planning
to live on campus next semester:
Please cometo ResLife to cancel your
housing. This is not necessary for stu 
dents living in fall-only housing! call
x7-3248 or e-mail
reslife@emerald.tufts.edu
Make Some Plans Before Going
Abroad
Maybe you should lead an Explo 
rations/Perspectives seminarIn the
fall. See the ExColiege office for
more Info.
WInter Recess
On-Campus residents should check
their mailboxes for VERY IMPOR-
TANT winter recess info.
Questions?Go on-line to
ase.tufts.edu/reslife, email
reslife@emerald.tufts.edu or stop by
ResLife, South Hall, ext. 7-3248
Fratemltfes*Sororltles*Clubs*Student
Groups
Earn $1,000-$2,000 this semester
with the easy CIS three hour
fundraising event. No sales required.
Fundraising dates are filling quickly,
so call (800)797-5743 today, and
leave a message for eric at x 108.
Music Dept. Events Week of 11/29
12/2 Tufts Chamber Singers.
Alumnaue Hall 8pm
12/2 Wind Ensemble, Cohen Audito 
rium,8pm
12/3 Third Day Gospel Choir. Cohen
AUditorium, 8pm
12/4 Orchestra and Chorale. Cohen
Audnorium, 8pm
Survivor Support Group
A drop-in support group for women
whose lives have been touched by
physical and/or sexual violence,
Come to listen, talk and/or friendly
support in a confidential and safe en 
vironment.
Mondays, 7-8:15pm in the Women's
Center Lounge, 55 Talbot Ave.
HOUSING
Staying around this summer?
Secure Housing Now! 3 bdrs available
in a gorgeous 3 bedroom house. 10
Dearborn 2 min walk to campus cen 
ter, gym and Davis. 2 bath, furnished,
For more info call Danielle at 718 
9496.
Semi-retired, Elderly Professor
has room near campus
For spring semester, (and after). Mod 
est rent in addnion to very minimal re 
sponsibilnies to help care for profes 
sor and home. Many Amennies avail 
able. Male student please call (781)
395-1384.
Female Student Looking
for short term housing for Jan and
Feb. before stUdying abroad. Summer
sublet is also desired. Please call Jes
X1745.
For Sale
For Sale
Great students housing 6 ft. Queen
Sleep Sofa. Blue Leather. Best Offer.
Call Julie 617 628-8151.
SERVICES
Need extra cash?
Have fun working wnh children in their
own homes. Backup babysitting &amp; af 
ter school care. $9-$12.hr, Childcare
references required. Call Joy 617 
739-KIDS. Parents in a Pinch, Inc.
SIZE DOES MATTER
BIGGEST BREAK PACKAGE
BEST PRICE FROM $29
WWW.SPRINGBREAKHQ.COM
1-800-224-GULF
Free CD
Free CD of Cool Music when you reg 
ister at my bites.com, the Ultimate
website for your college needs.
Extra Income for '99
Earn $500-$1000 weekly stuffing en 
velopes. For details RUSH $1.00 wnh
SASE to: Group Five, 6547 n. Acad 
emy Blvd, PMB-N. Colorado Springs,
Co 80918.
#1 Spring Break VacationsI
#1 Spring Break Vacations! Best
Prices Guaranteed!!! Cancun, Ja 
maica, Bahamas &amp; Florida! Book
Early &amp; recieve Freee Meal Plan. NoW
Hiring Campus Reps! 1-800-234 
7007. www. endlesssummertours.
com
Spring Break 2000 with STS
Join America's #1 Student Tour Op 
erator to Jamaica, Mexico, Bahamas,
Cruises and Florida. Now hiring on 
campus reps. Call 1-800-648-4849 or
visit us online@ www.sts.travel.com
Go Dlrectll
We're the Amazon.com of Spring
Break! #1 internet based company
offering Wholesale pricing byeliminat 
ing middlemen! We have other corn 
panies begging for mercy! Servicing
ALL destinations. Guaranteed Lowest
Price! 1800 367-1252.
www.springbreakdirect.com
SPRING BREAK 2000
The Millennium: A new decade...nce
in Travel. Free trips, Free Drinks, Free
Meals Jama ica, Cancun, Florida, Bar 
bados, Bahamas. Book Before Nov.
5 for Free Meals and 2 Free Trips!
1800426-7710/
www.sunsplashtours.com
Relationship Problems?
Stud~'Problems? De-
pressed?
Dr. Richard A. Goodman,
"Newsweek" quoted therapist and re 
lationship specialist has a few open 
ings for students. Complete confiden 
tiality. Tufts insurance accepted. Call
(617) 739-2'550.
SPRING BREAK 2000'
Largest selection of spring Break Des 
tinations, inclUding Cruises! Cancun,
Bahamas, AcapUlco, Jamaica, Ve 
gas, Florida &amp; MORE. foam parties,
Free Drinks, and Club Admissions.
Rep posniolls and Free Trips avail 
able. Epicurean tours 1-800-231-4 
FUN
Airport Sipecial to Logan $20
Please call for resel'Vations. Visa MIC
AlEx welcome. Serving Arlington and
surrounding areas. Call 781-646 
0088 for taxi service.
SPRING BREAK 20001
Cancun, Bahamas, Jamaica, Florida,
&amp; South Padre. Call USA Spring
Break today for the best prices and
packages to the most popular Spring
Break destinations! 1-888-777-4642
(or) www.usaspringbreak.com
Medford Bed and Breakfast
Turn of the Century homes with el 
egant, warm and homey atmosphere.
Quiet back streets. Located close to
#94 bus.Ab~ut1.25 miles form cam 
pus. Call Bill or Linda at (781) 396 
0983. Rates: 1 night - single, 95 
double, 110; 2-5 nights - single, 95  
double 105; weekly - single, 525  
double, 575.
Grad School Applications
Expertly Typed (Law,
Business, Medical, etc.)
***396-1124*"
Are your grad school applications
piled high 01 your desk? Are you
wonderingh,~wyou're going to fit all
your info in those tiny spaces? Are
you concerned where you'll find the
time to do n /111 before the deadlines?
Is your Personal Statement and Re 
sume professionally typeset and la 
ser printed 011 high-qualny paper in a
typestyle that's attractive? No need
to fret - CALL FRAN at 396-1124, a
specialist in making your applications,
personal stat.ement, and resume as
appealing as possible.
"Resumes"
Laser Typeset
$30.00 396-1124
Impressive Laser Typeset Resumes
featuring computer storage for future
updating. Your choice of typestyles
including bold, nalics, bUllets, etc, on
Strathmore paper. Have your cover
letters done by us to match your re 
sume! One-day service avail. 5 min.
from Tufts (member of PARW: Pro 
fessional Assoc. of Resume Wrners.
Call for FREE Resume/Cover Letter
Guidelines). Also word processing or
typing of student papers, grad school
applications, personal statements,
theses, multiple letters, tapes tran 
scribed, laser printing, fax services,
etc. CALL FRANCES at 396-1124.
AM RESUME SERVICE
*"Word Processing and
Transcription Service***
(781) 396-1124
Student papers, theses, grad school
applications, personal statements,
tape transcription, resumes, graduate!
faculty projects, multiple letters,
AMCAS forms. Thorough knowledge
of APA, MLA, and Chicago Manuals
of Style. All documents are laser
printed and spell checked using
WordPerfect. Reasonable Rates.
Quick turnaround. Serving TUFTS
students, faculty for over 10 years. 5
min. for Tufts. Call Fran at 396-1124
(Member of NASS, National Assoc.
of Secretarial Services) AM WORD
PROCESSING
WANTED
Semester Break Work
$15.00 base - appt. Special 1-5
week wonk progam In Customer
Sales/Service. flex hours.
conditions apply. Apply NOW!
call 781 891-0177 or apply on line.
www.wonkforstudents.com
Wanted: Female Personal Care
Assistant
3 hours in moming/3 hours at night.
$9.50Ihr. Duties inclUde showering,
laundry, meal preparation, and feed 
ing. No Lifting Involved!! Located in
Everett Sq. Public transportation ac 
cessible. For directions/other informa 
tion call Ted (617) 389-0476
Premed Volunteer
as Office/Research Assistant NEMC
n!searcherlclinical doctor needs help
in office with medical article review/
organizatioin, data entry and filing.
Call Gloria Green at (617)636-0772.
Chlldcare Positions
Local families looking for enthusiatic
students to provide care and
mentorship for children wnh develop 
mental disabilnies. Gain valuable ex 
perience and make a difference!!
Transportation preferred, $10-$12 per
hour. Call Emily Osborne at EMARC
(781) 942-4888.
Computer Programmer
Part-time computer programmer
needed for small startup com.
Proficient in Perl, CGI and Unix a
must, knOWledge of email systems
helpful. Student applicants welcome.
Flexible hours. E-mail
admin@birdmail.com
Business Help Wanted
Real EstateAsslstant needed to
wonk with active salesperson at
high volume office near Tufts.
Part-time 15 hrslwk over 5 days.
Call 617 623-2500 X322 or 617
666-3459. Ask for Irene.
Are you a proud Greek?
We are looking for a few outstanding
Greeksto market ournewinformation
service to chapters around the country.
You would do research on other
chapters then communicate with the
chapter officers. Flexible hours.
Flexible locations - On orOffcampus.
Experience as a chapter officer is a
plus. Outgoing, motivated candidates
only. Contact Scott Akerman at
College Solutions, Inc. 617 242-8644
or email: sherman99@prodigy.net
BABYSITTER
Work @ home mother looking for sit 
ter to watch newbom approx. 20 hI'S
a week M-F. Transportation and Holi 
days not a problem. Start ASAP. Sal 
ary based on experience. Interested?
Contact Mark or Kelly @ 781-391 
3314.
Seeking Experlenced Child Care
Provider
for fun and lively children ages 2 and
4 on Tuesdays and Thursdays from
9:30-3:30. We live near Davis Square.
Pay starting at $10/hr. will increase
to $12 if all goes well. Call 354-4703
Teacher Wanted
for three adorable 2-year-olds, We
need a provider for this playgroup on
Wednesdays from 11 :00-4:00 and on
Fridays from 9:30-3:30. Live near bike
path between Davis Sq. and Alewife.
Call 661-1156. $101hr.
Babysitter Wanted
Work @ home Mother looking for sit 
ter to watch newborn baby approx. 20
hrslwk. M-F. Transportation and holi 
days not a problem. Start ASAP. Sal 
ary based on experience. Interested?
Contact Mark Orkelly at 781 391 
3314.
Babysitter Needed:
Seeking experienced and loving
babysitterfortwo adorable girls-infant
and 2 year old. Fun household. Flex 
ible hours. Great pay! Call 781-279 
1189 in Stoneham.
Receptionist. Afternoon Hours
$10+/hr. 2:30-5:30pm., 3 days per
week. Some f1exibiltty in hours is pos 
sible, parlicular days can be arranged.
Addnional hours/days may be avail 
able if desired. Duties include greet 
ing visnors and answering incoming
telephone calls. Requires good tele 
phone voice and professional de 
meanor. Dependabilny and punctual 
ity are extremely important. Located
near Burlington Mall. Contact Kathy
Riley at XENERGY Inc. 781-273 
5700. http://www.xenergy.com
NowHlrlng
HANNAH's 499 Broadway. Hannah's
the areas newest restaurant/bar and
billiard club wants you for all shifts and
positions. Apply in person or call M-F
10:00-4:00 (617) 629-5302.
Carlng Women Needed to be Egg
Donors
ages 21-30, compensation is $3,000
for time and effort given in donating.
Call Dr. Figueroa II-free 1 888 494 
4060 for an information packet.
Counselors sought
for unique, prestigious summer camp
for chilidren around the world. Spec 
tacular coastal location in Maine, on
both fresh water take and ocean. Spe 
cialists needed for 30+activ~ies,in 
cluding: trip leaders, equestrians,
photographers, swimmers, tennis,
gymnastics, basketball, baseball, la 
crosse, golf, riflery, and sailing; ar 
chers, fishermen, kayakers, canoe 
ists, naturalists, marine biologist; vi 
sual, musical, dramatic and martial
arts; rock climbing, roller hockey,
skateboarding. Interview in Medford,
Cambridge and Boston. Inquire early.
Salary structure dependent on exper 
tise. Starting at $1800 for nine weeks.
For more info email Daniel:
Staff@Robinhoodcamp.com
Experienced Babysitter
Wanted
for baby and small child. Part time,
hours vary for occasional weekend
eves, in clean relaxed home near
Davis Sq. T. Seeking Fun, energetic,
responsible person wnh references.
Non-smoking. 625-3119.
Free Baby Boom Box and
Earn $12001
Fund-raiser for student group and or 
ganizations. Earn up to $4 per
MasterCard app. Call for info or visit
our websne. Qualified caller receive
a FREE Baby Boom Box 1 800 932 
0528 ext 119 or ext 125
www.ocmconcepts.com.
EGG DONOR SOUGHT:
$10,000 COMPENSATION
We are a happily married couple ea 
ger to become parents. If you are a
compassionate individual with very
high intelligence, an appealing per 
sonality, and good health, please
send your confidential response to PO
Box 4366 Highland Park NJ 08904 
4366
All Tufts students must submit c1assifieds in person, prepaid with cash or check. All c1assifieds must be submitted by 3 p.m. the day before publication. Classifieds may also be bought at the Infonaation Booth at the Campus Center. All classifieds submitted by mail
must be accompanied by a check. Classifieds may not be submitted over the phone. Notices and Lost &amp; Founds are free and run on Tuesdays and Thursdays only. Notices are limited to two per week per organization and run space pennitting. Notices must be written
on Daily fonns and submitted in person. Notices cannot be used to sell merchandise oradvertise major events. The Tufts Daily is not liable for any damages due to typographical errors or misprintings except the cost ofthe insertion. which is fully refundable. We reserve
the right to refuse to print any classifieds which contain obscenity. are ofan overtly sexual nature, or nre used expressly to denigrate a person or group.
ministertohold in theeventdisar 
mament had not begun by Febru 
ary.
His lieutenant, Ken Maginnis,
told the crowd that a "no" vote
would likely mean isolation for
Northern Ireland's Unionists. The
British, American, and Irish gov 
ernments would wash their hands
of them, delegates recalled him
saying.
"This is the lesser oftwo evils
and we'vegotto give it a try," said
Tom Davison, 83, a delegate from
Bangor who said he made up his
mind after listening to the
speeches.
Trimble, Adams barter deal
UNIONISTS
I
to advertise in the Dally
call (617)627-3090
continued from page 9
majorityTrimble'scamphad hoped
to get, but enough to declare vic 
tory overopponents in his divided
party.
Key to his success was the
support ofhis deputy, John Tay 
lor, who originally spoke out
against the deal but came around
in the eleventh hour.
Trimble told the delegates Sat 
urday that they would never get a
better opportunity to bring the
anned conflictto an end. Then, he
said he had given the party presi 
dent a letter ofresignation as first
back from its 0-2 start tomorrow
at Suffolk. Sheldon is confident
in his team's ability to put the
losses behind and move on, and
the Jumbos are looking to be
above the .500 mark by the time
they return home to face MIT on
Dec. II.
"We set a team goal to win the
next four, and we think we can do
that," he said. "We need to tweak
some things, and some pieces
aren't quite there yet, one ofthose
being Bobby Mpuku. We'rehappy,
but we're 0-2, so we're not too
happy."
dentat Kabul University, charged.
"Many people who did atrocities
here during the warare allowed to
live in the United States. Why
cannot we ask for them to be turned
over to us?"
Muttawakil, the foreign minis 
ter, asserted thatthe United States
"is known as the world's police 
man, butnow those police are kill 
ing our people with missiles and
hunger.... I don't know ifOsama
bin Laden is a hero ornot. But now
the United States has made him
into a big hero."
"Paul Smithhad a greatgame,"
Sheldon said. "They had trouble
stopping him and right from the
beginning he was on fire. They
had match-up troubles, and we
saw that and got the ball to him.
That was nice to see because I
think he's going to have a good
year for us.
"An older experienced team
came through in the end and won
it, though" he continued, "but I
was happy with the wayweplayed.,
As far as I'm concerned, it was a
goodgamethatwejustdidn'twin.'"
The team will look to bounce:
financing the Afghan resistance
against occupying Soviet troops
during the 1980s.
The United Statesheavilybacked
that resistance, but afterthe Taliban
militiaseized Kabulin 1996 and im 
posedharsh Islamic laws, Washing 
ton turned againstthe regime. Now,
efforts to capture bin Laden have
depressed relations further.
"For America, bin Laden was
an angel when he was in the holy
war against the Soviets, but now
they say he is a spy and a terror 
ist," Mohammad Mirwaiz, a stu-
continued from page 7
Aside from the turnovers,
Sheldon is happy with his team's
perfonnance. The Jumbos out 
shot RPI56,4 percent to 41.2 per 
cent, and held a 36-29 advantage
on the boards. Senior Paul Smith
had a huge game for the team,
contributing 22 points and six re 
bounds, while sophomore Bobby
MacMannis went 3-5 from three
pointrange on hiswayto 11 points.
Junior Fred Pedroletti led the way
ontheboards, pulling down seven
rebounds.
Jumbos will look for first 'win tomorrow
BASKETBALL
United Nations sanctions hurt civilians
AFGHANISTAN
continued from page 9
by mail from relatives abroad, a
majorsourceofincorne in a coun 
try where most people do not
have jobs, and doctors, for ex 
ample, earn less than $5 per
month. Since all flights into the
country are barred, people must
travel to Pakistan to pick up
mailed money.
Some people in Kabul accused
the United States this past week of
being hypocritical in its pursuit of
bin Laden, an important figure in
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_12" n="12" type="page">
<p>J J J).' J,. ,., ..&#8226; , ... ",
'\ '-' -' -').'
12
THE TUFTS DAILYe November 29, 1999
&#8226;
11/29199
12 13
54 Louise or Turner
56 Glass container
57 Vocalized grunt
59 Put a lid on it
60 Brink of
Christmas
61 Primary color
&amp;;7
HE: NEVfER FOl.JGHT
WITH HI';l WIFe:
~fECAU?fE?HfE
KNfEW HOW TO ---
46 Displays
47 Comprehend
48 Fine mist
49 Play pranks
50 Stays in the
military
53 Gin flavoring
a 3 3 NI'N"[Nt S N&#8226; 3 S
3~I~1 Vl31N 1 I 1 N n
1 v~n~3111 I 1 I 1 1 I W
S~3 g 8 V r ....3 S~3 A V
--gsa d. 3 aa0
S1S3Na~V138~
,~tl.H S 3 0 1 vHIi~~
.~~l:I 3 1 1 V~Sl:I~,!.
~v~0 N 3 S. S 0~d
S 3 1 I W 3 S. A wlw v S
S N~n.~.1v 3_
a I 3 N 3 V S 3 S 1 3 S 1
N3A3LIINl 3A";" SL3S
v 1 I A 3 0 a 3 l:I A V M V
H S~v W S v~~S~0~
fl'il~NlID1t~THAT SCRAMBLED WORD GAME
~~~~@by Henri Arnold end Mike Arlllrion
Unscramble these four Jumbles, You're right as always, dear
one letter to each square, to form~;5
four ordinary words. c$f!!/ -I&lt; 18
~e~
..--rt.JC"r
~
=*
28
, 999 Tribune Media Services, Inc.
All rights reserved.
65
62
31
55
36
52
40
14
17
Now arrange the circled letters to
form the surprise answer, as sug 
gested by the above cartoon.
Prtntanswerhere: (TIIJrnITIJ
(Answers tomorrow)
saturday's IJumbles: TWICE FINIS GYPSUM STUPID
Answer: What the law students studied at the
pool-SWIM 'SUITS'
8 Son of Seth
9 Squeal
10 Residue
11 Hilo hello
12 Geneva's lake
13 List components
19 Geneva's
populace
21 Obstacle to free
speech
23 Build up
24 Anwar of Egypt
25 Ray
26 Surefire shots
27 Goon snow
29 Crude crosses
30 Alphabet start
33 Unbumt brick
34 Stellar blasts
35 Canines, e.g.
37 Two-wheeler
38 First Shaker
41 Loop of land
42 Small indefinite
amount
43 Toblarne
44 Charles or Alben
!DailyCrossword
ACROSS
1 Piece of broken
pottery
6 'The Cloak" or
'The Bat"
11 Boxer
Muhammad
14 Check recipient
15 Bones in
forearms
16 Net-judge's call
17 Guinness and
Baldwin
18 Delicious
20 Stop or flood
ending
22 Unexpected hit
23 Javelin
26 Most people?
28 Skedaddling
31 John or John
Quincy
32 Showing
deference
36 Took chairs
37 Coalitions
39 Rabbit female
40 Kept balanced
43 Higher
45 Guesses
48 liming-signal light
, 51 Give vigor to
.52 Strip
53 Unbroken stretch
55 "Kiss of the
Spider Woman"
star
58 Digestive disorder
62 African snake
63 Extreme
discomfort
64 Take a powder
65 Affirmative
66 Ostrich kin
67 Prefigured
DOWN
1 Fatfarm
2 Kubrick's
compu1er
3 First-mate's
affirmative
4 Take back
5 Fashion creations
6 Land more
punches
_7. Secret plan
~
C)
~
-I
2
Q.
ID
III
c:
Aquarius (Jan. 20-Feb. 18) - Today is a 7- You're facing a bit of a dilemma.
If you go off with your friends, you'll have lots of fun. You migbtspend more
than you can afford, however. Either come up with another source of income
or another group of friends to play with!
Pisces (Feb. 19-March 20) - Today is a7- Things are changing, and that
might make you nervous. To increase your own personal stability, figure out
what you want to make happen. It's difficult to get where you want to go if you
have no idea where that is! Set agoal.
r.:::THA===T="'=EAN===&amp;===:::::;:-' i r::R=E="'=E"'=BE==R=,=,(=o=u:::::::--'
FAL&amp;IF'fING THE f CAN'T &amp;PELL
FOLLOWING DOC-~CO"'PLIANCE
U"'ENT&amp;: Q&amp;R, ! WITHOUT &#183;LIANCE:
APOP, FMEA. MSA. !
&amp;pe. PPAP AND Q&amp;A.
WOOtIOO.' IT'S 'THE
WEEIe AFliR
THANkS&amp;IVIN6!
IN ADDITION TO
1&amp;0 '1000, WE WILL
&amp;Tll.IVE TO BE
Q&amp;-'1000 CO"'PLIANT.
Virgo (Aug. 23-Sept22) - Today is a7- You're interested and interesting now. You
could find out something that you've been wondering about for along time. Ask
leading questions, and you may get the infonnation you seek. It may come from an
unexpected source, however.
!:GI
Libra (Sept. 23-0ct. 23) - Today is a7- Some nice people help you out.
That's good. The bad news is that your plan isn't worked through completely.
Aries (March 21-ApriI19) - Today is a7- The back-to-work theme is appropriate Maybe you ought to wait alittle while before launching this project Back to the
'cause there's way too much to do. Pay c1uo;e attention to detail, too. Now that you know drawing board!
it'simportan~you can move your quality control check to top priority.
Scorpio (Oct. 24-Nov. 21) - Today is a7- You have apretty good scheme
Taurus (April20-May 20) - Today is an 8- You'll most likely feel mellow today. in mind. Discuss it just alittle bit more before you proceed. Security isimportan~
You'll be able to tackle even adifficult topic. Don't won)' even if there isn't enough and that's not part of the equation yet. Take the time to forge aframework you
money for everythingyou'd like. There seems to be plenty oflove, and that's way more can build upon.
important
Leo Guly 23-Aug. 22) - Today is a7- You can anticipate aconflict today, most likely
about money. Ifyou're generating the income, you get to say how it's spent. If it's the
other way around, you'd better dummy up. That looks rather unlikely, however.
Sagittarius (Nov. 22-Dec. 21) - Today is an 8- There's atest today, so watch
Gemini (May 21-June 21) - Today is a7- Lots of changes are underway. Are you out You may be called to account for somethingyou've done recently. Or, ifyou
and your partner having atiff? Are you thinking about moving or rearranging your haven't done it, you'll need to explain why not. Have the facts and figures at
furniture? Some planning is in order. !tmay not be easy, but later you'll sure be glad your fingertips, and you'll wow 'em.
that you did it.
Capricorn (Dec. 22-Jan. 19) - Today is a7- You have agrand trine in earth
Canoer Gune 22-]uly 22) - Today is a7- You're learning qUickly today, and that's signs now. That makes you even better at business and more practical than
good. You have to do that to keep up with anew and unfamiliar chore. This will be fun, usual. No matter what happei1s, you will most likely make aprofit. So, get busy!
almost, once you're used to the routine. Keep at it. You're almost there.
AROUND CAMPUS
THE TUFfS DAll..Y - THE ONLY
Society for Creative Anachronism
Get Medieval with us!
Weekly Meetings -Wednesdays
Dewick- meet by the couches, 6pm
o
Yrograms Abroad
General Info. Mtg.
Eaton 204, 3:30pm
WEDNESDAY
"Diplomacy is the art 0/saying 'Nice doggie' untilyou can find a rock. "
UniversityChaplaincy
Reflections on the Spiritual Quest
"Women in Waiting: Birthing the Christ"
Speaker: Rev. Miriam Acevedo, Associate
Chaplain
Goddard Chapel, 12:00-1 :Ollpm
*
TOMORROW
Vietnamese Students Club
Pan-Asian Fashion Show
HotungCafe
Spm&#183;
TODAY
Environmental Consciousness
Outreach
Weekly Meeting
Oxfam Cafe, 9:30 p.m.
RFASON TO COME BACK FOR FINAI..S
- Will Rogers
Late Night at the Daily
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
