<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Alliance for Progress or Alianza para el Progresso?  A Reassessment of the Latin American Contribution to the Alliance for Progress</title>
<author>Roberto Porzecanski</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>No publication information is avaliable</p>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Produced by: Acrobat Distiller 6.0.1 for Macintosh</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Generated from a source PDF document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date>2005-04-01T04:23:45 -0500</date>
	      Created by: Word: cgpdftops CUPS filter</creation>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2005-04-01T04:58:57 -0500</date>
<respStmt>
<name>unknown person</name>
</respStmt>
<item>unknown changes</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 id="page_1" n="1" type="page">
<p> &#13;
ALLIANCE FOR PROGRESS OR &#13;
ALIANZA PARA EL PROGRESO? &#13;
A REASSESSMENT OF THE LATIN AMERICAN &#13;
CONTRIBUTION TO THE ALLIANCE FOR PROGRESS &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy Thesis &#13;
Submitted by Roberto Porzecanski &#13;
Spring 2005 &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
&#169; 2005 Roberto Porzecanski &#13;
 &#13;
http://fletcher.tufts.edu &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_2" n="2" type="page">
<p>1 &#13;
 &#13;
INTRODUCTION: THE TRADITIONAL APPROACH, A NEW APPROACH &#13;
 &#13;
On March 13&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961, President John F. Kennedy gathered the representatives of the &#13;
Latin American governments in the White House to officially ask them &#8220;to join in a new &#13;
Alliance for Progress -Alianza para Progreso- a vast cooperative effort, unparalleled in &#13;
magnitude and nobility of purpose, to satisfy the basic needs of the American people for &#13;
homes, work and land, health and schools.&#8221;&#13;
1&#13;
 With those words, one of the most outstanding &#13;
periods in inter-American history had formally begun. The Alliance for Progress (henceforth &#13;
the Alliance) was a remarkable venture.&#13;
2&#13;
 It was evidently so, in President Kennedy&#8217;s words, &#13;
because it was unparalleled in magnitude &#8211;it aimed to direct 20 billion dollars of foreign &#13;
economic aid to Latin America in a period of 10 years- and nobility of purpose &#8211;as it &#13;
pursued very ambitious social objectives. It was also so because, as a consequence, it was &#13;
received with unparalleled expectations and, though this could be foreseen at the time, was &#13;
followed by unparalleled disappointment. &#13;
 &#13;
The Alliance&#8217;s remarkableness, as well as and the expectations and the disillusionment it &#13;
generated, made it the subject of a substantial amount of research, study and analysis. The &#13;
Alliance has been looked at extensively from as almost as many perspectives as possible: its &#13;
origins, its institutional instruments, its implementation, and its results. However, the &#13;
Alliance&#8217;s origins, by which I mean its conceptual foundations and its evolution as a policy, &#13;
                                                &#13;
1&#13;
 John F. Kennedy, &#8220;Address at a White House Reception for Members of Congress and for the Diplomatic &#13;
Corps of the Latin American Republics,&#8221; March 13&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961 in Theodore Sorensen, ed., &#8220;Let the Word Go Forth&#8221; &#13;
The Speeches, Statements and Writings of John F. Kennedy (New York: Delacorte Press, 1988), 352.  &#13;
2&#13;
 A full description of what was the Alliance for Progress is beyond the scope of this paper. In this paper, I will &#13;
assume the reader is familiar with its central elements. A full and thorough description of the Alliance and all its &#13;
elements can be found in L. Ronald Scheman, &#8220;Concept and Creativity,&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress: A &#13;
Retrospective, ed. L. Ronald Scheman (New York: Praeger, 1988.) &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_3" n="3" type="page">
<p>2 &#13;
despite having been extensively researched and written about, have not been accurately &#13;
portrayed.  &#13;
 &#13;
I will argue that this is the case because most studies of the origins of the Alliance&#13;
 &#13;
for &#13;
Progress suffer from a common shortcoming: they have approached the Alliance looking at &#13;
it exclusively as a policy of the United States government (henceforth the United States-&#13;
centric approach.) These studies have taken President Kennedy&#8217;s invitation to the Latin &#13;
Americans to &#8220;join&#8221; in a new Alliance for Progress literally, therefore looking at the Alliance &#13;
as something that was conceived in the United States to be presented to the Latin American &#13;
countries.  &#13;
 &#13;
The Alliance for Progress, an alternative definition &#13;
 &#13;
If the Alliance for Progress was not an American&#13;
3&#13;
 policy, then what was it? The &#13;
Alliance can, theoretically, be defined in two different ways: it can be defined as a specific &#13;
proposal of the Kennedy administration or, differently, as an inter-American policy. &#13;
Undoubtedly, named as such, the Alliance for Progress&#13;
4&#13;
 was a specific proposal of the &#13;
Kennedy administration. But, clearly, the Alliance was much more than that. If President &#13;
Kennedy&#8217;s words wouldn&#8217;t have been well received and acted upon in Latin America, we &#13;
would not be thinking about the Alliance for Progress today. As a consequence, I will argue &#13;
                                                &#13;
3&#13;
 Although in the context of inter-American relations the term &#8220;American&#8221; may not be the most appropriate &#13;
word to refer to something of United States origin, I will still use it with this connotation for purposes of &#13;
simplicity.   &#13;
4&#13;
 For a detailed account of the origin of the name, see: Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr. A Thousand Days: John F. &#13;
Kennedy in the White House (Boston and New York: Mariner Books, 2002,) 193. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_4" n="4" type="page">
<p>3 &#13;
that the Alliance for Progress can only be understood as an inter-American policy,&#13;
5&#13;
 albeit &#13;
with an American name.  &#13;
 &#13;
More importantly, as we will see in the next pages, when we look at the origins of the &#13;
Alliance for Progress it will become clear that the Latin American participation in the &#13;
Alliance did not start with President Kennedy&#8217;s words. In fact, President Kennedy&#8217;s words &#13;
were the result of an inter-American dialogue that started in the early 1950s and that &#13;
involved both the Eisenhower and the Kennedy Administrations.   &#13;
 &#13;
Comparing approaches, broadening the perspective &#13;
 &#13;
Beyond being inaccurate, an additional problem of the United States-centric &#13;
approach to the history of the Alliance is that it provides incorrect interpretations. I will &#13;
argue that by looking at the Alliance exclusively as an American conception and therefore &#13;
focusing their attention entirely on the policy-making process in the United States, scholars &#13;
adhering to the United States-centric approach (henceforth scholars presenting the &#13;
&#8220;conventional interpretation&#8221;&#13;
6&#13;
) have only presented a partial picture about the origins of the &#13;
Alliance. As a result, the relative importance of the different factors that played a role in the &#13;
creation of the Alliance for Progress has been misrepresented. In particular, by looking at the &#13;
Alliance exclusively through the lens of American policy makers, scholars have generally &#13;
                                                &#13;
5&#13;
 Embodied in the &#8220;Charter of Punta del Este&#8221; the foundational document of the Alliance. The Charter of Punta &#13;
del Este is available from http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/intdip/interam/intam16.htm  &#13;
6&#13;
 Two examples are Roger Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the Alliance for Progress: Continuity and Change in US &#13;
Policy toward Latin America&#8221; (Ph.D. diss., Johns Hopkins University, 1976) and Gaddis Smith, The Last Years &#13;
of the Monroe Doctrine, 1945-1993 (New York: Hill and Wang, 1994.) &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_5" n="5" type="page">
<p>4 &#13;
characterized it as Cold War phenomenon, the response of the United States to challenges &#13;
posed by the Cold War in Latin America.  &#13;
 &#13;
In this paper, I will approach the issue of the origins of the Alliance for Progress in a more &#13;
comprehensive manner, focusing my attention not exclusively on the policy-making process &#13;
in the United States but also on the inter-American policy-making process. Among other &#13;
things, approaching the issue in such manner will shed light to the fact that although the &#13;
Cold War did play a role in the formulation of the Alliance for Progress, it was only one of &#13;
many factors that drove its adoption, together with true concerns with the conditions in &#13;
Latin America, which I believe to be the most important driving force behind what came to &#13;
be known as the Alliance for Progress.  &#13;
 &#13;
Those who approach the study of the Alliance for Progress from a United States-centric &#13;
approach have produced what I will call the &#8220;traditional account&#8221;&#13;
 7&#13;
  about the origins of the &#13;
Alliance, an account that is the direct result of exhaustively tracing the origins the Alliance &#13;
for Progress focusing almost entirely on the U.S. policy-making process. In this paper, I will &#13;
show that when the focus of study is broadened to include the inter-American policy-making &#13;
process, it will become evident that the traditional account provides incorrect assessments &#13;
about three important dimensions of the origins of the Alliance for Progress: its purpose, its &#13;
nature and its conceptual foundations.  &#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
7&#13;
 A detailed version of which can be found, for example, in: Harvey S. Perloff, Alliance for Progress, A Social &#13;
Invention in the Making (Baltimore and London: The Johns Hopkins Press, 1969) and Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the &#13;
Alliance for Progress.&#8221; &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_6" n="6" type="page">
<p>5 &#13;
The paper is organized in three sections. In the first section, I will present the &#8220;traditional &#13;
account&#8221; produced by those who study the Alliance from a United States-centric approach. &#13;
In the second section, I will provide a critique to this approach along the three mentioned &#13;
dimensions: purpose, nature and conceptual foundations. I will end with a conclusion.  &#13;
 &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_7" n="7" type="page">
<p>6 &#13;
THE TRADITIONAL ACCOUNT &#13;
 &#13;
Focusing exclusively on the policy-making process in the United States, scholars &#13;
have reached the consensus that the origin of the Alliance for Progress is to be found &#13;
somewhere in between the very end of the first or the early days of the second Eisenhower &#13;
Administration. These scholars point to the fact that Eisenhower&#8217;s original policy towards &#13;
the hemisphere slowly started to change as a result of a series of process unfolding and &#13;
particular events that took place.  &#13;
 &#13;
The early policy of the Eisenhower administration towards the Third World in general and &#13;
towards Latin America in particular was, roughly, twofold. In the security sphere, the policy &#13;
could be summarized as one that stressed military pacts and military aid to support &#13;
governments that were aligned with U.S. interest in the Cold War. In practice, this meant &#13;
governments that were actively opposed to all perceived, real or not, communist threat.  &#13;
 &#13;
In the economic realm, the policy was based on the belief that economic development would &#13;
only come as a result of the flow of private capital. Therefore, the U.S. assigned great &#13;
importance to the existence of governments that provided both the economic stability and &#13;
the legal security that were required for private capital (in particular, U.S. investments) to &#13;
flow and stay in Latin America.&#13;
8&#13;
 Almost tautologically, governments that fulfilled one &#13;
                                                &#13;
8&#13;
 The economic side of the &#8220;traditional&#8221; Eisenhower policy was also eloquently described by his most &#13;
important advisor regarding Latin American affairs, his brother Milton Eisenhower (who would later become &#13;
an advocate for change). Writing about his first trip to South America, in 1953, he describes the extent to &#13;
which, up to that point, the policy premises were unquestioned, even though he realized how critical the &#13;
situation in Latin America was: &#8220;I have given this abbreviated account of my visit in 1953 because I want to &#13;
emphasize as strongly as I can that both United States and Latin American leaders were then thinking solely in &#13;
terms of orthodox economic aid to Latin America as the solution to perplexing problems. By the end of the &#13;
trip I personally had become painfully aware of the need for social reform &#8211;for misery, poverty, ill health, and &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_8" n="8" type="page">
<p>7 &#13;
condition also fulfilled the other, as a belief in the importance of state action for &#13;
development (in the lines of land reform, for example) was perceived as a penetration of &#13;
communist ideas. &#13;
 &#13;
Reasons for Change &#13;
 &#13;
As said before, scholars have argued that a series of processes and particular events &#13;
started to question the adequacy of this approach to Latin American policy. The first of &#13;
these underlying processes is said to be the deterioration of the economic and social &#13;
conditions in Latin America, mainly driven by the important increase in population and by &#13;
the continuing deterioration of the economic situation in the different Latin American &#13;
countries. In the late 1950s these countries were facing a severe deterioration in their terms &#13;
of trade that was significantly slowing their economic growth, together with overwhelming &#13;
population growth and mass migration to the cities.&#13;
9&#13;
  &#13;
 &#13;
On top of that, scholars argue, in the mid 1950&#8217;s the Soviet Union started to realize that the &#13;
deterioration of conditions in Latin America and the inadequacy of U.S. policy to respond to &#13;
                                                                                                                                            &#13;
illiteracy obviously haunted the land like evil specters. But except for an uneasiness and a feeling of &#13;
compassion, I did not relate this to what we were doing and should do officially, except to hope that our efforts &#13;
might aid countries improve production and thus provide funds for internal social development. Certainly &#13;
instigating social change did not seem to be the responsibility of the United States.&#8221; Milton Eisenhower, The &#13;
Wine is Bitter; The United States and Latin America (Garden City: Doubleday, 1963,) 199.  &#13;
9&#13;
 More specifically, as Ronald Scheman points out summarizing the ideas presented in L. Ronald Scheman, &#13;
&#8220;Concept and Creativity&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, Scheman, 4: &#8220;As Walt W. Rostow points out &#13;
in Chapter 24&#8230; It was a young continent in which over half the population was under the age of 20 and was &#13;
rapidly approaching a job market in economies that were providing unable to generate employment. Mass &#13;
migration to the cities was transforming the countryside, as it was throughout the western world, resulting in &#13;
dismal urban sprawl and slum conditions. Forty million people were expected to migrate to the cities during the &#13;
1960s while job creation was proceeding at a pace that would produce only 5 million new jobs. Illiteracy &#13;
abounded. Agriculture lagged behind population growth, forcing increased food imports, while commodity &#13;
prices for Latin America&#8217;s exports, particularly coffee and sugar, were continually falling.&#8221;  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_9" n="9" type="page">
<p>8 &#13;
the challenges posed by that deterioration provided an opportunity to extend Soviet &#13;
influence to the Western Hemisphere. As Roger Leeds relates:  &#13;
 &#13;
In January 1956, the subject of growing communist influence shifted from Africa &#13;
and Asia to Latin America, when Soviet Premier Bulganin announced that his &#13;
country was prepared to expand economic and commercial ties with Latin American &#13;
countries. The Premier&#8217;s statement was particularly noteworthy because at that time &#13;
the Soviet Union had regular diplomatic relations with only three Latin American &#13;
countries &#8211;Argentina, Mexico and Uruguay. The [New York] Times interpreted the &#13;
statement as &#8216;the strongest bid to date to win an economic and commercial tie with &#13;
Latin America&#8217;.&#13;
10&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
Bulganin&#8217;s announcement was relevant, it is pointed out, not only because it signaled that the &#13;
Soviets recognized that the economic and social situation in Latin America provided an &#13;
opportunity to extend Soviet influence. His announcement was also relevant because it &#13;
awakened some Americans about the inadequacy of U.S. policy and how the economic &#13;
problems in the Americas could bear Cold War significance.  &#13;
 &#13;
In light of the rising challenge posed by the situation in Latin America and the new &#13;
communist strategy, a debate started to take shape in the political and policy-making circles &#13;
in the United States about what would be the most appropriate policy towards Latin &#13;
America, in particular, and the Third World in general. The key issue of this debate, that is, &#13;
the main point of argument and disagreement, was whether the policy that the Eisenhower &#13;
                                                &#13;
10&#13;
 Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the Alliance for Progress,&#8221; 46.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_10" n="10" type="page">
<p>9 &#13;
administration had pursued up to that point was appropriate in light of the new challenges or &#13;
if, to the contrary, a new approach was needed, and, if so, what should this new approach &#13;
look like.  &#13;
 &#13;
The debate about a new policy towards Latin America was to a certain extent part of a broader &#13;
debate regarding American policy towards the Third World, a debate in which the U.S. &#13;
Congress played a very significant role. In July 1956, the Senate created a Special Committee &#13;
to Study the Foreign Aid Program, Chaired by Senator Francis Green, a Democrat from &#13;
Rhode Island who would a year later become Chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee. &#13;
The hearings held by this Special Committee soon became a forum for the exchange of ideas &#13;
regarding the role that foreign aid would play if a new strategy towards the Third World was &#13;
adopted. As part of this debate, two M.I.T. economists that worked at the Center for &#13;
International Studies, Max Millikan and Walt W. Rostow, devised and articulated a new &#13;
strategy that placed a significant and crucial emphasis on a new foreign aid policy for the &#13;
United States. The core assumptions and recommendations of these two economists were &#13;
contained in a book published in 1957 called A Proposal; Key to an Effective Foreign &#13;
Policy,&#13;
11&#13;
 in which a case was advanced to significantly increase foreign aid as a foreign policy &#13;
tool, particularly for achieving Cold War policy objectives.&#13;
12&#13;
  &#13;
 &#13;
Specifically regarding Latin America, in simultaneous with the broad debate about a need for &#13;
a new strategy towards the Third World that took place in policy-making circles in &#13;
Washington, a similar process of reassessing the adequacy of the traditional Eisenhower &#13;
                                                &#13;
11&#13;
 Walt W. Rostow and Max Millikan, A Proposal; Key to an Effective Foreign Policy (New York: Harper, 1957.) &#13;
12&#13;
 The evolution of this debate is traced with extreme detail in Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the Alliance for &#13;
Progress.&#8221; &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_11" n="11" type="page">
<p>10 &#13;
policy happened on a more personal level, involving particular officials within the &#13;
Eisenhower administration. Specifically two officials, Milton Eisenhower, who advised the &#13;
President on Latin America, and Douglas Dillon, Under Secretary of State for Economic &#13;
Affairs in the late years of the Eisenhower Administration, realized early than most than a &#13;
change in policy was badly needed. &#13;
 &#13;
Milton Eisenhower, for example, spent the eight years of his brother&#8217;s Administration &#13;
dealing with Latin America and he had traveled extensively throughout the region. In those &#13;
years, he grew to realize that the policy that was being pursued was ineffective and started to &#13;
lobby, inside the administration, for a change.&#13;
13&#13;
  &#13;
 &#13;
But, scholars point out, while the deterioration of the economic and social situation in Latin &#13;
America, the change in the Soviet&#8217;s strategy and the availability of a new approach played a &#13;
significant role in the change of U.S. policy towards the region, a series of specific events &#13;
that were, nonetheless, related to the deterioration in conditions and to a growing &#13;
dissatisfaction with U.S. policy towards the region, provided the final stroke.  &#13;
 &#13;
The first of these specific events was what came to be known as Vice-President Nixon&#8217;s &#13;
failed trip to South America in May, 1958. As Harvey Perloff recounts:  &#13;
 &#13;
But the change in the U.S. view of Latin America did not come from logic. It came &#13;
as a result of the shock that followed the hostile and violent reaction to Vice &#13;
                                                &#13;
13&#13;
 A more detailed account of the evolution of the thinking of Milton Eisenhower and Douglas Dillon can be &#13;
found in: Eisenhower, The Wine is Bitter and C. Douglas Dillon, &#8220;The Prelude,&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A &#13;
Retrospective, Scheman, 63.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_12" n="12" type="page">
<p>11 &#13;
President Richard M. Nixon&#8217;s so-called &#8220;goodwill tour&#8221; of South America [probably, &#13;
to address the growing dissatisfaction with U.S. policy] in the spring of 1958. The &#13;
fact that a Vice President of the United States could be spat upon, insulted, and his &#13;
life threatened [in Venezuela], focused U.S. attention forcefully on the disintegration &#13;
of its Latin American policy.&#13;
14&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
The second of these specific events was something that came immediately after and to some &#13;
extent as a consequence of what happened to Nixon in Venezuela. Brazilian President &#13;
Juscelino Kubitschek used Nixon&#8217;s failed trip as a trigger to call for what he named &#13;
&#8220;Operation Pan America,&#8221; which essentially was a request for substantial financial assistance &#13;
from the United States targeted to the development of Latin America. Although this was not &#13;
the first time Kubitschek articulated an idea as such, the call for &#8220;Operation Pan America&#8221; was &#13;
certainly his more formal and visible proposal. &#13;
 &#13;
Moreover, President Kubitschek&#8217;s &#8220;Operation Pan America&#8221; essentially echoed and &#13;
articulated a widespread feeling in Latin America, particularly among democratically elected &#13;
officials and leaders of democratic forces, about the inadequacy of United States policy &#13;
towards Latin America, and put forward a relatively specific set of proposals for change. &#13;
Behind President Kubitschek&#8217;s proposal was the feeling that Latin America had been &#13;
forgotten in the post World War II years, particularly vis-&#224;-vis the American attitude towards &#13;
Europe embodied in the Marshall Plan.  &#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
14&#13;
 Perloff, Alliance for Progress, 13. Nixon&#8217;s own account of what happened in Caracas, Venezuela can be found &#13;
in Richard M. Nixon, Six Crises (Garden City, NY: Doubleday &amp; Company, Inc., 1962.) &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_13" n="13" type="page">
<p>12 &#13;
Finally, the last and perhaps most important event that is referred to as a trigger of change in &#13;
United States policy was the triumph of the Cuban Revolution, in January 1&#13;
st&#13;
, 1959. As &#13;
Perloff accounts: &#13;
 &#13;
The need for a new policy had been given urgency by the Castro victory in Cuba. As &#13;
his government and the Cuban press increasingly anti-American and pro-Communist &#13;
in tone during 1959 and 1960, U.S. policy shifted from a position of patience and &#13;
tolerance. In March, 1960, President Eisenhower approved initial work on a &#13;
contingency plan to overthrow the Castro regime. Four months later, while U.S. &#13;
embassies were reporting from all parts of Latin America that the Castro victory was &#13;
exciting interest in a revolutionary approach to winning long-denied reforms from &#13;
the ruling elites, President Eisenhower said the United States would support &#13;
sweeping reforms in Latin America with financial assistance. The Latin Americans &#13;
were quick to respond.&#13;
15&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
A new policy emerges &#13;
 &#13;
It is evident, by Perloff&#8217;s account, that by late 1959 the American policy towards &#13;
Latin America had gone through a deep revision. This revision resulted in a new policy that &#13;
produced the creation of the Inter-American Development Bank, something the Latin &#13;
Americans had been insistently requesting for long and finally took place in 1959, that took &#13;
President Eisenhower on a goodwill trip to South America in February, 1960, but, most &#13;
                                                &#13;
15&#13;
 Perloff, Alliance for Progress, 16. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_14" n="14" type="page">
<p>13 &#13;
importantly, that drove to the adoption of the Act of Bogot&#225;&#13;
16&#13;
 with full American support. &#13;
The Act of Bogot&#225;, approved by the Council of the Organization of American States on &#13;
September 13, 1960, recommended &#8220;Measures for Social Improvement and Economic &#13;
Development within the Framework of Operation Pan America&#8221; and established, by &#13;
decision of the United States &#8220;a special inter-American fund for social development&#8221; for &#13;
which Congress had previously authorized 500 million dollars.  &#13;
 &#13;
Leeds&#8217; main conclusion about the Act of Bogot&#225; is worth quoting because it underscores all &#13;
the elements in which the United States-centric approach fails to fully grasp, as we will see, &#13;
all the elements that played a role in the creation of the Alliance for Progress. About the Act &#13;
of Bogot&#225;, he says: &#13;
 &#13;
[It] came after eight years in which government officials gradually shifted their &#13;
outlook about the importance of the hemisphere to the Cold War struggle with the &#13;
Soviet Union. Also, it came only after Congress had debated the issues and &#13;
tentatively concluded that aid to developing countries was an important device in the &#13;
United States arsenal of weapons to combat perceived Soviet threats. And finally, the &#13;
Act of Bogot&#225; signaled that the Administration felt reasonably confident that the &#13;
American people had at least concluded that a large foreign aid program was &#13;
acceptable and even important in terms of U.S. national interest.&#13;
17&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
16&#13;
 A full text of the Act of Bogot&#225; is available from &#13;
http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/intdip/interam/intam08.htm &#13;
17&#13;
 Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the Alliance for Progress&#8221; 187.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_15" n="15" type="page">
<p>14 &#13;
About this same process, Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr.&#13;
18&#13;
 has said: &#13;
 &#13;
The combination of [Douglas] Dillon, Milton Eisenhower and, in 1959, Fidel Castro &#13;
finally began to have its effects. The Cuban revolution convinced Dillon that the &#13;
United States simply could not go into another hemisphere meeting without solid &#13;
recommendations of its own to lay on the table. When President Eisenhower &#13;
returned from his own Latin American trip early in 1960, Dillon persuaded him in &#13;
June to take a new step and propose American assistance in establishing a &#13;
hemisphere fund for social progress.&#13;
19&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
The Kennedy Administration &#13;
 &#13;
For Eisenhower, there was little time left after the Act of Bogot&#225; was adopted. Two &#13;
months later John F. Kennedy was elected President and both the rhetoric and the &#13;
commitment of the United States towards Latin America were revolutionized, although &#13;
clearly building on the process just described.&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
President Kennedy talked about a new Alliance for Progress in his inaugural speech, in his &#13;
first State of the Union address and on the evening of March 13&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961, when he gathered &#13;
the representatives of the Latin American governments in the White House to officially &#13;
launch the Alliance. After a few months and several preparatory meetings, the Charter of &#13;
                                                &#13;
18&#13;
 Special Assistant to President John F. Kennedy, involved, among other things, in Latin American policy.  &#13;
19&#13;
 Schlesinger, A Thousand Days, 190. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_16" n="16" type="page">
<p>15 &#13;
Punta del Este&#13;
20&#13;
, the founding document of the Alliance, was adopted on August 17&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961 &#13;
in Uruguay.   &#13;
 &#13;
It has been bitterly debated whether President Kennedy&#8217;s Alliance for Progress proposal &#13;
represented the logical and unavoidable next step to what had been done during the late &#13;
years of the Eisenhower Administration or, to the contrary, if President Kennedy actually &#13;
substantively modified the policy of the previous administration.&#13;
 21&#13;
 To illustrate this debate, I &#13;
will present two contrasting views that show the most important arguments advanced by &#13;
both sides. For example, while Milton Eisenhower has argued that:  &#13;
 &#13;
A critical reading of those addresses [in reference to the addresses President &#13;
Eisenhower gave in his late Latin American trip], of his special message to Congress &#13;
in August 1960 (conceived on the trip), and of several talks made later by President &#13;
Eisenhower, will convince even an ardent political partisan that the Alliance for &#13;
Progress proposal made by President Kennedy in 1961 did not envision a major shift &#13;
in policy; on the contrary, it was the logical next step in our constantly evolving &#13;
programs.&#13;
22&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
On the other hand, Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr. has said that the Alliance for Progress proposal &#13;
represented a revolution in U.S. policy towards Latin America, even in light of the late &#13;
moves of the Eisenhower administration: &#13;
                                                &#13;
20&#13;
 The Charter of Punta del Este is available from &#13;
http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/intdip/interam/intam16.htm &#13;
21&#13;
 A detailed and objective discussion of what elements of continuity and change existed between the Alliance &#13;
for Progress as proposed by Kennedy and the developments that preceded it is beyond the scope of this paper. &#13;
This has been done thoroughly by Roger Leeds in: Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the Alliance for Progress.&#8221; &#13;
22&#13;
 Eisenhower, The Wine is Bitter, 12.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_17" n="17" type="page">
<p>16 &#13;
 &#13;
Under the prodding of Douglas Dillon, Milton Eisenhower and, more specially, Fidel &#13;
Castro, the Eisenhower Administration had come by 1960 to support the Act of &#13;
Bogot&#225; and asked Congress to appropriate $ 500 million for social development in &#13;
Latin America. The Alianza went considerably beyond this to lay down three goals &#13;
for the hemisphere: long-term economic development, structural reform, and &#13;
political democratization.&#13;
23&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
I believe that an objective assessment of the history undoubtedly points to the fact that &#13;
President Kennedy&#8217;s proposal for an Alliance for Progress, while clearly building on the &#13;
shifts in Latin American policy that took place in the late years of the Eisenhower &#13;
administration (embodied in the Act of Bogot&#225;,) represented an innovation in terms of &#13;
American commitment (both rhetorical and financial) and in terms of the breadth of the &#13;
agenda.  &#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
23&#13;
 Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., &#8220;Myth and Reality,&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, Scheman, 67.  &#13;
 &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_18" n="18" type="page">
<p>17 &#13;
A CRITIQUE &#13;
 &#13;
What is missing in the picture presented so far? As said before, the United States-&#13;
centric approach has two problems. The first is one of accuracy. As I explained before, the &#13;
Alliance was not an American policy but an inter-American policy, and its study should be &#13;
approached as such.   &#13;
 &#13;
The second problem with the United States-centric approach, also mentioned, is that it &#13;
provides incorrect interpretations in emphasizing that the Alliance for Progress&#8217; purpose was &#13;
to prevent communist and Soviet infiltration in Latin America; that the most important &#13;
characteristic of its nature was its form, a massive aid program, and not its policy &#13;
recommendations; and, finally, that its conceptual foundations are to be found in a new theory &#13;
about the role of foreign aid in foreign economic policy and not in a new theory of &#13;
development in Latin America.  &#13;
 &#13;
Purpose  &#13;
 &#13;
I shall argue that the main purpose of the Alliance for Progress was not, as scholars &#13;
argue, to prevent Fidel Castro&#8217;s assertion that the Andes would become the Sierra Maestra of &#13;
South America. Of course, counter-communism and the prevention of revolution, by &#13;
providing an appealing &#8216;revolutionary&#8217; alternative, were undoubtedly part of the intentions of &#13;
the United States in changing its policy towards Latin America, both in the Eisenhower and &#13;
the Kennedy years. This rationale should not be underestimated, as the officials involved in &#13;
the Alliance have publicly acknowledged. Moreover, the generous commitment of funds by &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_19" n="19" type="page">
<p>18 &#13;
the United States Congress to the Alliance for Progress can hardly be understood without &#13;
this underlying justification.  &#13;
 &#13;
But, even within the United States, counterrevolution was not the sole objective being &#13;
pursued by the change in policy. There is strong evidence that points to the fact that many &#13;
of the American officials involved in the creation and implementation were genuinely &#13;
committed to Latin America, and saw a change in policy as the &#8216;right thing to do.&#8217; This was &#13;
the case in the Eisenhower years, as eloquently expressed by Milton Eisenhower: &#13;
 &#13;
We should remember that the Alliance was evolved largely without reference to &#13;
Castro-communism, that the program would be imperative even if there were no &#13;
communist threat, that it is wholly in harmony with our deepest religious and &#13;
democratic convictions, and that our abiding purpose in positive, not negative. But &#13;
the Alliance is, coincidentally, our best hope for smothering the evil that seeks to &#13;
destroy the concept of associated free nations and to substitute an absolute &#13;
reminiscent of social man prior to the dawn of human freedom.&#13;
24&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
There is also strong evidence that in the Kennedy years many of those who worked on the &#13;
Alliance also shared a vision in which security and Cold War concerns were not the exclusive &#13;
driving force. This has been argued, for example, by Lincoln Gordon, a member of the &#13;
Kennedy transition task force that dealt with Latin America: &#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
24&#13;
 Milton Eisenhower, &#8220;The Alliance for Progress, Historic Roots&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress, Problems and &#13;
Perspectives, ed. John C. Dreier (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1962), 23. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_20" n="20" type="page">
<p>19 &#13;
Alongside these negative motivations [in reference to counter communism &#13;
motivations] was the positive side &#8211;the hopes for a major advance in social and &#13;
economic development in a region of long standing special interest to the United &#13;
States. For me and for most North Americans initiators of the Alliance, these &#13;
positive expectations were the dominant force behind our actions. That may surprise &#13;
listeners in the 1980s when superpower rivalries are again so prominent. It can be &#13;
understood only against the background of the Kennedy Administration&#8217;s wider &#13;
policies of aid for the world&#8217;s underdeveloped regions &#8211;in part ideological, but also, &#13;
in the famous phrase of the inaugural address, &#8220;because it is right.&#8221;&#13;
25&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
In sum, a careful look at the purposes of those in charge of putting together the Alliance, &#13;
even if we restrict the analysis to the policy-making process in the United States, portrays a &#13;
much nuanced and comprehensive picture about the origins of the Alliance, a picture in &#13;
which Cold War considerations were clearly not the only driving force.  &#13;
 &#13;
But, if we take the analysis one step further, and look at the inter-American policy-making &#13;
process instead of looking exclusively at the policy-making process in the United States, we &#13;
see clearly that counter communism was not the main driving force behind the Alliance for &#13;
Progress. Ironically, this is even recognized by those who more strongly defend the pure &#13;
Cold War rationale for the Alliance for Progress. For example, Howard J. Wiarda, while &#13;
arguing one the one hand that &#8220;the Alliance for Progress was a direct response and &#13;
outgrowth of the Cuban revolution&#8230;. this was not just some starry-eyed, altruistic, &#13;
                                                &#13;
25&#13;
 Lincoln Gordon, &#8220;The Alliance at Birth: Hopes and Fears&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, &#13;
Scheman, 74. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_21" n="21" type="page">
<p>20 &#13;
humanitarian giveaway program, as it was sometimes portrayed at the cartoon level and as &#13;
some of its supporters actually believed,&#8221;&#13;
26&#13;
 at the same time acknowledges that: &#13;
 &#13;
A powerful and earlier impetus to the Alliance had also come from Latin America. &#13;
As early 1955 President Juscelino Kubitschek of Brazil had began to call for a vast &#13;
program of assistance to and self help for Latin America, which he [later] called &#13;
&#8220;Operation Pan-America&#8221; and which incorporated most of the main elements of the &#13;
Alliance. He was later joined by President Alberto Lleras Camargo of Colombia in &#13;
pushing for such a program. Other Latin American presidents advocated similar &#13;
measures. The founding in 1959 of the Inter-American Development Bank, a &#13;
regional, multilateral, but largely U.S.-funded assistance bank, was an integral part of &#13;
the same campaign. Indeed, one of the unique aspects of the Alliance as an &#13;
assistance program was the degree to which it initially grew out of, and particularly &#13;
incorporated, ideas emanating from Latin America.&#13;
27&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
Wiarda&#8217;s argument is important for two reasons. Firstly, because it underscores the extent to &#13;
which the Alliance was the result of an inter-American policy-making process (something &#13;
that, I would argue, by this point should be beyond any question.) As such, it becomes &#13;
evident that one should look for the motivations behind the Alliance for Progress not only &#13;
among American policy makers but also among Latin American policy makers. And about &#13;
that there is widespread agreement that the motivation was not a counter communist one, &#13;
but a true concern for addressing the key development issues facing Latin America. For &#13;
                                                &#13;
26&#13;
 Howard J. Wiarda, &#8220;Did the Alliance &#8216;Lose Its Way,&#8217; or Were Its Assumptions All Wrong from the &#13;
Beginning and Are Those Assumptions Still with Us?&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, Scheman, 99. &#13;
27&#13;
 Ibid., 96.  &#13;
 &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_22" n="22" type="page">
<p>21 &#13;
Latin Americans, the Alliance&#8217;s main and most important objective was development as an &#13;
end, not as a means. The purpose was not to reduce the incentives for Communist &#13;
revolutions throughout the hemisphere; it basically was to take their countries out of the &#13;
situations of stagnation and despair in which they were immersed. In addition, Latin &#13;
Americans were trying to set up the conditions for democracy for flourish and stabilize, &#13;
which they saw highly correlated with economic development, a vision they shared with their &#13;
American counterparts.  &#13;
 &#13;
The second reason for which Wiarda&#8217;s argument is important is because is highlights the &#13;
extent to which the substantive provisions of the Alliance emanated from Latin America. I &#13;
will come back to this point later, when I discuss conceptual foundations.   &#13;
 &#13;
I believe it is patently clear that when we approach the Alliance for Progress from a &#13;
comprehensive perspective, it becomes evident that its main purpose was not to prevent the &#13;
spread of communism or revolutions &#8216;Castro style&#8217; in Latin America. On the contrary, the &#13;
most important objective being pursued was the achievement of a significant improvement &#13;
in the conditions for Latin America, economically, socially and politically. I argue that this is &#13;
the case not only because this was certainly the overarching most important objective for &#13;
one of the two partners in the Alliance (Latin America) but also because many of the policy &#13;
makers in the United States (including, to a great extent, President Kennedy) were also, &#13;
essentially, pursuing the same objective. The fact that both objectives could to some extent &#13;
be achieved simultaneously should not obscure the relative importance of the two different &#13;
motivations. &#13;
 &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_23" n="23" type="page">
<p>22 &#13;
Once again, the importance that counter communism played in the creation of the Alliance, &#13;
essentially in the United States, should not be ignored.  However, broadening the perspective &#13;
displays the relative importance of this motivation. The problem of the United States centric &#13;
approach, as I said, is one of emphasis. &#13;
 &#13;
Nature &#13;
 &#13;
Beyond misrepresenting the purposes of the Alliance, emphasis is wrongly placed by &#13;
scholars in a second important dimension of the Alliance for Progress: its nature. To explain &#13;
what I mean by nature, let me go back to President Kennedy&#8217;s words on March 13&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961, &#13;
when the Alliance for Progress was presented as &#8220;a vast cooperative effort, unparalleled in &#13;
magnitude and nobility of purpose, to satisfy the basic needs of the American people for &#13;
homes, work and land, health and schools.&#8221;&#13;
28&#13;
 The issue at stake here is: what was the most &#13;
important characteristic of the Alliance, its &#8220;magnitude&#8221; or its &#8220;nobility of purpose&#8221;? A &#13;
possible answer to this question is that the question itself is irrelevant, that the exceptionality &#13;
of the Alliance was such because it was both unparalleled in magnitude and nobility of &#13;
purpose. Although it is hard to disregard this argument, I will argue that comparing the &#13;
relative importance of &#8220;magnitude&#8221; &#8211;the amount of funds involved- and &#8220;nobility of &#13;
purpose&#8221; &#8211;the ambitious social objectives of the Alliance- is important in the sense that it &#13;
sheds new light on the origins of the Alliance.  &#13;
 &#13;
Scholars have constantly argued that the most important feature of the Alliance was its &#13;
magnitude and, to support this claim, they point to the exceptionally ambitious goal that the &#13;
                                                &#13;
28&#13;
 John F. Kennedy, &#8220;Address at a White House Reception for Members of Congress and for the Diplomatic &#13;
Corps of the Latin American Republics,&#8221; March 13&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961 in Sorensen, ed., &#8220;Let the Word Go Forth&#8221;, 352. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_24" n="24" type="page">
<p>23 &#13;
Alliance established. As Roland Scheman points out, &#8220;The daring ambitions of the Alliance &#13;
were to channel to the region $20 billion in foreign assistance in a decade, with $10 billion &#13;
coming from official sources and $10 billion from private sources.&#8221;&#13;
29&#13;
 The Alliance aimed to &#13;
entail, undoubtedly, an unprecedented financial effort, both in general and specifically in &#13;
terms of the American commitment. By focusing on the United States, and seeing such a &#13;
deep and unmatched financial commitment to Latin America, scholars concluded that this &#13;
was the most striking feature of the Alliance.  &#13;
 &#13;
However, if we analyze the substantive elements of the Alliance for Progress&#13;
30&#13;
 even from a &#13;
pure American perspective, it becomes strikingly clear that if the American financial &#13;
commitment was unprecedented, its support for the substantive policies involved in the &#13;
Alliance was much more so. Regarding these substantive policies and for purposes of my &#13;
argument, the summary provided by Scheman is descriptive enough: &#13;
 &#13;
The Charter of Punta del Este, signed on August 17&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961, set forth 94 specific &#13;
objectives toward national economic and social goals, according to the Organization &#13;
of American States. They covered almost every aspect of social and economic &#13;
activity. They ranged from the major objective of achieving sustained economic &#13;
growth by raising per capita income not less than 2.5 percent a year, to more general &#13;
goals of social justice and more equitable income distribution. In a number of areas &#13;
specific targets were set forth, such as reform of tax and agrarian structures, &#13;
                                                &#13;
29&#13;
 L. Ronald Scheman, &#8220;Concept and Creativity&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, Scheman, 8. A much &#13;
more detailed discussion about the economic aspects of the Alliance for Progress can be found in this chapter.  &#13;
30&#13;
 I understand that an argument can be made that the magnitude was also a substantive element, and I will &#13;
tend to agree with that assertion. However, for analytical purposes, I will treat the magnitude and the &#13;
substantive elements separately.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_25" n="25" type="page">
<p>24 &#13;
provision of low-income housing and health services, strengthening of labor &#13;
organizations, and the achievement of economic integration.&#13;
31&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
It is impossible to overestimate the radical departure that the support by the United States to &#13;
progressive tax and land reform, strengthening of labor organizations and Latin American &#13;
integration represented from previous United States policy. Even when looking exclusively &#13;
at the American side of the Alliance for Progress, it is clear that its most striking &#13;
characteristic was not its magnitude but the policies it committed the United States&#8217; support &#13;
to.  &#13;
 &#13;
But, if we, once again, take the analysis one step further, and look at the nature of the &#13;
Alliance from a Latin American perspective, it becomes even more evident that the most &#13;
outstanding characteristic of the Alliance for Progress was not the enormous amount of &#13;
resources that would be poured into the region by a previously reticent United States &#13;
(although that element can hardly be underestimated) but the fact that the U.S. was not only &#13;
willing to accept but to support policies (such as land reform, Latin American integration, &#13;
etc.) that until recently had seen with much suspicion.    &#13;
 &#13;
I believe it is now clear, in light of the preceding discussion, that while the Alliance for &#13;
Progress was unprecedented both in its magnitude and in its substantive policy &#13;
recommendations the most striking characteristic about it, both from a change in U.S. policy &#13;
                                                &#13;
31&#13;
 L. Ronald Scheman, &#8220;Concept and Creativity&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, Scheman, 12. Most of &#13;
the same substantive elements were already present in the Act of Bogot&#225;. For a thorough comparison between &#13;
the two documents (the Charter of Punta del Este and the Act of Bogot&#225;, see: Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the &#13;
Alliance for Progress.&#8221;  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_26" n="26" type="page">
<p>25 &#13;
perspective and from a Latin American perspective, were the specific policy &#13;
recommendations that were included as an integral part of the Alliance.  &#13;
 &#13;
The immediate logical question that follows this assertion is: why is this important? It is &#13;
important because the Alliance&#8217;s magnitude and the Alliance&#8217;s substantive provisions have &#13;
very different conceptual foundations. While the foundations for a massive program of &#13;
foreign aid are partially to be found in the United States, the foundations for the substantive &#13;
provisions involved in the Alliance undoubtedly came from Latin America. The fact that the &#13;
most striking characteristic of the Alliance were its substantive provisions not only speaks &#13;
about the purposes of the Alliance, but also highlights the crucial role that Latin America &#13;
played in its formation. A more detailed discussion of this issue will make the case even &#13;
stronger.  &#13;
 &#13;
Conceptual Foundations &#13;
 &#13;
Two different sets of ideas played part, to different degrees, in the formulation of the &#13;
Alliance for Progress. These are, on the one hand, the ideas that Max Millikan and Walt &#13;
Rostow developed and articulated in their book A Proposal and, on the other, what has &#13;
grown to be called structuralism, a truly indigenous current of Latin American thought about &#13;
the development problems of Latin America, spearheaded by the work that Argentinean &#13;
Economist Ra&#250;l Prebisch did in the framework of the ECLAC, the United Nations &#13;
Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean. A brief summary is necessary &#13;
to illuminate the discussion that will follow.  &#13;
 &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_27" n="27" type="page">
<p>26 &#13;
I have already briefly touched upon the ideas articulated in Millikan and Rostow&#8217;s A &#13;
Proposal,&#13;
32&#13;
 saying that the core argument of the book (and the theory behind it) was that &#13;
foreign economic aid should be given a much important role as a foreign policy tool, &#13;
particularly for achieving Cold War policy objectives. Additional important elements were &#13;
the requirement of government planning in the receiving countries and the assurance that &#13;
the economic aid offered should be guaranteed for at least several years, as &#8220;even quite a &#13;
large program will lose most of its effectiveness if it teeters along on the verge of &#13;
Congressional disapproval with no more than a one-year lease on life.&#8221;&#13;
33&#13;
 Interestingly, &#13;
beyond advocating for an increase in foreign aid and requiring temporal stability and &#13;
planning in the receiving countries, the proposals of Millikan and Rostow did not advance &#13;
any other policy recommendations for the potential receiving countries. &#13;
 &#13;
On the other hand, the ideas of what is known as &#8220;structuralism&#8221; can be traced back at least &#13;
to the mid 1940s although its founding document, Ra&#250;l Prebisch&#8217;s El desarrollo econ&#243;mico &#13;
de la America Latina y algunos de sus principales problemas&#13;
34&#13;
, was published in 1949. In &#13;
brief, structuralism advocated industrialization and programs of price stabilization as ways of &#13;
overcoming the structural problem of the deterioration of terms of trade for Latin America, &#13;
progressive redistribution of wealth, land reform, the need to improve the technological &#13;
capacity and infrastructure, the importance of national planning and the need for the &#13;
creation of a Latin American common market. Finally, structuralism recognized the need for &#13;
                                                &#13;
32&#13;
 Rostow and Millikan, A Proposal.  &#13;
33&#13;
 Ibid., 67.  &#13;
34&#13;
 Ra&#250;l Prebisch, &#8220;El desarrollo econ&#243;mico de la Am&#233;rica Latina y algunos de sus principales problemas&#8221; in La &#13;
Obra de Prebisch en la CEPAL, ed. Adolfo Gurrieri (Mexico: Fondo de Cultura Econ&#243;mica, 1982.) &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_28" n="28" type="page">
<p>27 &#13;
an important increase in foreign funds to supplement the insufficient internal resources &#13;
existing in Latin America.&#13;
 35&#13;
   &#13;
 &#13;
Scholars adhering to the conventional interpretation of the origins of the Alliance, by &#13;
looking exclusively at the policy-making process in the United States, and seeing as the &#13;
Alliance&#8217;s most outstanding feature its magnitude as a foreign aid program, have pointed to &#13;
the theory advanced by Millikan and Rostow as the conceptual foundation of the Alliance &#13;
for Progress.  &#13;
 &#13;
However, even if we agreed with the assessment that the Alliance&#8217;s most outstanding feature &#13;
was its magnitude as a foreign aid program it is important to recognize that the claims by &#13;
Latin Americans that a new inter-American policy was needed and that such a policy would &#13;
necessary involve an increase in U.S. development assistance clearly predated the diffusion of Millikan &#13;
and Rostow&#8217;s ideas. President Kubitschek call for &#8220;Operation Pan-America,&#8221; which was &#13;
formalized with a letter to Eisenhower in 1958, was far from being his first attempt to &#13;
request an increase in U.S. assistance. &#13;
 &#13;
In addition, at the beginning the link between Millikan and Rostow&#8217;s ideas and the problems &#13;
of Latin America was, at best, weak. There is strong evidence that the theory presented by &#13;
Millikan and Rostow was clearly developed not thinking about Latin America but about &#13;
other areas of the world, particularly India and South East Asia. This is evident not only &#13;
because nowhere in their book can a mention to Latin America be found, but also by the &#13;
                                                &#13;
35&#13;
 A thorough description of structuralism can be found, for example, in: Victor Urquidi, The Challenge of &#13;
Development in Latin America, trans. Marjory Urquidi (New York: Praeger, 1964.) &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_29" n="29" type="page">
<p>28 &#13;
fact that in 1958 when then Senator John F. Kennedy, advised by Rostow,&#13;
36&#13;
 attempted to &#13;
turn the broad debate taking place in the Senate into a more concrete proposal he put &#13;
forward a bipartisan initiative that would come to be known as the Kennedy-Cooper &#13;
Initiative, aimed at providing enlarged and long-term international support for the economic &#13;
development of India.  &#13;
 &#13;
Moreover, when we switch our focus to what I have argued was the most important element &#13;
of the Alliance, its substantive recommendations, there can be no doubt that the Alliance &#13;
owns its policy prescriptions, embodied in the Charter of Punta del Este, to the ideas of &#13;
structuralism. A simple comparison of the structuralist literature and the Charter of Punta &#13;
del Este (and to some degree, the Act of Bogot&#225;) would render this evident. However, this &#13;
wasn&#8217;t how it was perceived at the time (and to a great extent, it is not how it is perceived &#13;
today), what drove Ra&#250;l Prebisch himself, in an article written in 1963, to stress the point: &#13;
 &#13;
Indeed, the basic ideas underlying this document [in reference to the Charter of &#13;
Punta del Este] were conceived and gradually developed over a period of years in &#13;
Latin America. For a long time we have constantly maintained the view that a &#13;
vigorous movement of industrialization was imperative in the process of &#13;
development. We have also reaffirmed the inevitability of land reform and other &#13;
changes in the social structure, in order to facilitate the massive adoption of modern &#13;
technology and the progressive redistribution of the fruits of development. We called &#13;
                                                &#13;
36&#13;
 A thorough account of Kennedy&#8217;s interest in India can be found in: Walt W. Rostow, Eisenhower, Kennedy &#13;
and Foreign Aid (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1985.) About Rostow&#8217;s influence on Kennedy, Leeds has &#13;
said: &#8220;In the case of Professor Rostow, a close association with John Kennedy developed at the same time his &#13;
ideas about foreign economic assistance were gaining increasing credibility. According to the M.I.T. professor, &#13;
beginning in early 1958 &#8216;I became Senator Kennedy&#8217;s principal advisor on foreign economic policy&#8230; This was &#13;
well before other intellectuals began to jump on the Senator&#8217;s bandwagon&#8217;.&#8221; Leeds, &#8220;The Origins of the &#13;
Alliance for Progress,&#8221; 108.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_30" n="30" type="page">
<p>29 &#13;
the attention to the importance of terms of trade, and the need to counteract their &#13;
tendency to deteriorate through transformations in the economic structure; and we &#13;
insistently advocated measures to attenuate their fluctuations. The idea of the Latin &#13;
American Common Market emerged in our countries. And the need for a &#13;
considerable enlargement in foreign funds to supplement a more intense &#13;
mobilization of internal resources in order to accelerate the rhythm of development, &#13;
was also preached for a long time in Latin America.  &#13;
 &#13;
Moreover, though facing strong opposition, we, the Latin Americans, were the ones &#13;
that launched the idea of the need for systematic planning as a means to act in a &#13;
conscious and deliberate way upon the economic and social forces and thus expedite &#13;
the achievement of the great goals of development in an orderly and progressive &#13;
fashion. In times that are not yet far behind some of these ideas encountered very &#13;
strong resistance, which was frequently couched in intractable and dogmatic terms. &#13;
Now they are recognized as sound and valid and are largely embodied in the Charter &#13;
of Punta del Este. However, there has developed a rather peculiar tendency to &#13;
present these ideas as having been conceived in the United States, or as constituting &#13;
a ready made American blueprint to be applied in Latin America. I am really &#13;
concerned about this trend, for not only is it contrary to the facts, but its political &#13;
implications are highly detrimental to the Alliance itself and to the broad popular &#13;
support it requires in Latin America.&#13;
37&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
37&#13;
 Ra&#250;l Prebisch, &#8220;Economic Aspects of The Alliance&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress, Problems and Perspectives, ed. &#13;
Dreier, 25. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_31" n="31" type="page">
<p>30 &#13;
Prebisch&#8217;s words are eloquent, and I believe them to be particularly important for two &#13;
reasons. Firstly, because they show that the spirit and the core foundations of the Alliance &#13;
for Progress are to be found more than anywhere in the structuralist paradigm. Moreover, as &#13;
important as the conceptual influence that structuralist thought had in the formation of the &#13;
Alliance, its imprint was also felt at a more practical level. Two examples will illustrate this.  &#13;
 &#13;
At the institutional level, between President Kennedy&#8217;s Alliance for Progress speech (March, &#13;
1961) and the Conference of Punta del Este (August, 1961), very significant preparatory &#13;
work for the conference took place. In this context, the most important preparatory &#13;
document that was elaborated for the Conference of Punta del Este was called Planning for &#13;
Economic and Social Development for Latin America&#13;
38&#13;
 and was written, in the framework &#13;
of the General Secretariat of the Organization of American States (Pan American Union), by &#13;
a Group of Experts, most of them strongly affiliated with structuralist thought and assisted &#13;
by Ra&#250;l Prebisch and Osvaldo Sunkel of ECLAC. The substantive proposals contained in &#13;
that document, which was circulated to all countries before the conference, were not only a &#13;
manifestation of structuralist thought but also prefigure almost entirely the provisions of the &#13;
Charter of Punta del Este. &#13;
 &#13;
The influence that Latin Americans had in the Alliance for Progress in general and in the &#13;
drafting of the Charter of Punta del Este in particular becomes even clearer when we look at &#13;
the communication between Richard Goodwin, Kennedy&#8217;s Assistant Special Counsel and &#13;
the President. Although in his published account of the origins of the Alliance for Progress&#13;
39&#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
38&#13;
 Pan American Union, Planning for Economic and Social Development for Latin America, Washington, D.C., 1961.  &#13;
39&#13;
 Richard N. Goodwin, Remembering America: A Voice From the Sixties (Boston: Little Brown and Company, &#13;
1988.) &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_32" n="32" type="page">
<p>31 &#13;
he barely makes any reference to the Latin American influences on the project, the records &#13;
of his communications with the President show that influence with clarity:  &#13;
 &#13;
During the same week in April [in reference to the week of April 14&#13;
th&#13;
, 1961], Lincoln &#13;
Gordon and I met in Rio with Jorge Sol (Chief of the IA-ECOSOC&#13;
40&#13;
 staff), Raul &#13;
Prebisch (Chief of the UN Commission for Latin America), and Felipe Herrera &#13;
(President of Inter-American Bank). Out of this intensive series of discussions, &#13;
lasting a week, emerged a general consensus of the objectives of the July meeting &#8211;&#13;
what we hoped to accomplish, a proposed agenda, and the manner in which the &#13;
preparatory work should be organized.&#13;
41&#13;
  &#13;
 &#13;
At a more personal level, the influence and the degree of involvement that Ra&#250;l Prebisch &#13;
himself had with those planning the Alliance for Progress in the United States can be seen &#13;
through the eyes of Adolf Berle, an American diplomat with a long and outstanding career &#13;
who was asked to chair the Latin American task force, the transition group in charge of &#13;
advising President Kennedy in Latin American policy. In his diary entry for December 10th, &#13;
1961, he wrote:  &#13;
 &#13;
December 10 continued. To take Ra&#250;l Prebisch (Argentine Economist) out to &#13;
breakfast. This pursuant to instructions from Senator Kennedy&#8217;s office&#8230;. He &#13;
[Prebisch] said the whole job was to give economic and social content to the idea of &#13;
freedom, and that a strong statement by Kennedy along those lines would be a great &#13;
deal of help to him&#8230;. In his view, this was an historical moment and required &#13;
                                                &#13;
40&#13;
 Acronym for Inter-American Economic and Social Council &#13;
41&#13;
 Goodwin to Kennedy, 12 June 1961, FRUS, 1961-1963 12: 27. &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_33" n="33" type="page">
<p>32 &#13;
everyone to get on board&#8230;. ECLA contemplates a closed common market for Latin &#13;
America. I asked whether the United States might come in on it-opening its own &#13;
markets now to Latin American manufacture against their commitment to reduce &#13;
their tariffs on our manufactured goods over a period of X years. This brought him &#13;
all up standing (he is alleged to be anti-American) and he thought it would be &#13;
wonderful.&#13;
 42&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
Moreover, Prebisch&#8217;s words are important because they highlight the negative consequences &#13;
that the conventional interpretation of the origins of the Alliance entails. As he said, the &#13;
perception that the Alliance was something created in the United States would to a great &#13;
extent undermine a very much needed support for the enterprise in Latin America. Of &#13;
course, Prebisch&#8217;s was not taking in theoretical terms; he knew what the reaction in Latin &#13;
America had been and would be if the perception of the American imposed Alliance for &#13;
Progress prevailed. An example will clearly illustrate this.  &#13;
 &#13;
If popular support for the Alliance was important throughout Latin America, in 1961 it was &#13;
particularly important in Uruguay, where the Conference that would launch the Alliance was &#13;
due to take place. On the eve of the Conference of Punta del Este, Vivi&#225;n Trias, the leading &#13;
figure of Uruguay&#8217;s socialist party wrote:  &#13;
 &#13;
The idea of utilizing the international organizations and the advice of &#8220;chemically &#13;
pure&#8221; technicians to cover the looting of the resources and the interests from &#13;
investments that allow extracting 4 dollars for each dollar invested was gaining &#13;
                                                &#13;
42&#13;
 Beatrice Bishop Berle and Travis Beal Jacobs ed., Navigating the Rapids 1918-197; From the Papers of Adolf A. &#13;
Berle (New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., 1973,) 721.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_34" n="34" type="page">
<p>33 &#13;
momentum [&#8230;]. Between the gestational process of the Conference of Punta del &#13;
Este and the preparation of the aggression to the revolutionary Cuba there a clear &#13;
dialectic link. [&#8230;]. On March 13th and in a speech delivered to the Latin American &#13;
diplomatic corps in the White House, Kennedy announces his Alliance for Progress. &#13;
On April 14th he makes public his intention to gather the CIES [in reference to the &#13;
Inter-American Economic and Social Council] in the middle of the year and on the &#13;
17th the landing in the Bay of Pigs takes place [&#8230;]. Behind the smiling and childish &#13;
face of this new image of Pan Americanism, behind the interested propaganda &#13;
implicit in the Alliance for Progress the usual imperialism is the driving force [&#8230;]. &#13;
The Alliance for Progress is a complete expression of the neo imperialism of the &#13;
United States, adapted to the condition of its structural crisis and projected on the &#13;
background of the Cuban revolutionary process.&#13;
 43&#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
It is clear that, as Prebisch said, a misconception about the origins of the Alliance could &#13;
certainly undermine its support in Latin America and, consequently, its effectiveness.  &#13;
 &#13;
                                                &#13;
43&#13;
 Vivi&#225;n Trias, El Plan Kennedy y el desarrollo de Am&#233;rica Latina (Montevideo, Uruguay: Ediciones del Sol, 1961), &#13;
210. Cited in Adolfo Garc&#233;, Ideas y Competencia Pol&#237;tica en Uruguay (1960-1973): Revisando el &#8220;fracaso&#8221; de la CIDE &#13;
(Montevideo: Ediciones Trilce, 2002), 46 (my translation.) The original text in Spanish reads as follows: &#8220;La &#13;
idea de utilizar los organismos internacionales y el asesoramiento de t&#233;cnicos &#8220;qu&#237;micamente puros&#8221; para &#13;
encubrir el saqueo de las materias primas y de los intereses de las inversiones que permiten extraer 4 d&#243;lares &#13;
por cada uno invertido fue tomando cuerpo [&#8230;]. Entre el proceso gestador de la Conferencia de Punta del &#13;
Este y la preparaci&#243;n de la agresi&#243;n a la Cuba revolucionaria hay una vinculaci&#243;n dial&#233;ctica n&#237;tida. [&#8230;]. El 13 de &#13;
marzo y en un dicurso pronunciado ante el cuerpo diplom&#225;tico latinoamericano en la Casa Blanca, Kennedy &#13;
anuncia su plan de Alianza para el Progreso. El 14 de abril hace p&#250;blico su prop&#243;sito de reunir al CIES para &#13;
mediados de a&#241;o y el 17 se produce el desembarco en Playa Gir&#243;n [&#8230;]. Tras la cara sonriente y ani&#241;ada de esta &#13;
nueva imagen del Panamericanismo, tras la propaganda interesada impl&#237;cita en la Alianza para el Progreso, &#13;
alienta el imperialismo de siempre [&#8230;]. La Alianza para el Progreso es una expresi&#243;n cabal del neoimperialismo &#13;
estadounidense, adaptada a la coyuntura de su crisis de estructura y proyectada en el transfondo del proceso &#13;
revolucionario cubano.&#8221;  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_35" n="35" type="page">
<p>34 &#13;
The Alliance for Progress&#8217; conceptual foundations: a conclusion  &#13;
 &#13;
As with the assessment regarding purpose and nature, the conventional assessment &#13;
about the conceptual foundations of the Alliance for Progress misrepresents the relative &#13;
importance that different factors played. I believe it should now be evident that the Alliance &#13;
was, more than anything, a child of structuralist thought and it is there where its essential &#13;
conceptual foundations are to be found.  &#13;
 &#13;
This does not mean that I believe Millikan and Rostow&#8217;s ideas played no role in the &#13;
formulation of the Alliance for Progress. The broader discussion about the need to increase &#13;
foreign economic aid although originally was not inspired in Latin America did help pave the &#13;
way for a program such as the Alliance for Progress, as it was instrumental in convincing &#13;
public officials in both the executive and legislative branches that foreign economic aid could &#13;
be an important element in the toolbox of U.S. foreign policy. &#13;
 &#13;
Moreover, Rostow slowly became more and more interested in Latin America and started to &#13;
advocate the application of his ideas to the western hemisphere. He finally played an &#13;
important role in the creation of the Alliance, both through his ideological influence on &#13;
Kennedy and as a policy maker himself, as in the Kennedy Administration Rostow acted as &#13;
Deputy Special Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs (1961) before &#13;
becoming Chairman of the Policy Planning Council at the Department of State (1961-1966.) &#13;
But the shape that the Alliance took, its very nature, its most revolutionary and substantive &#13;
provisions are clearly a materialization of structuralist thought. Without that conceptual &#13;
foundation, the Alliance wouldn&#8217;t have existed.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_36" n="36" type="page">
<p>35 &#13;
CONCLUSIONS &#13;
 &#13;
I started this paper saying that the origins of the Alliance for Progress, despite having &#13;
been extensively studied and written about, had not been portrayed with full accuracy. I &#13;
argued that this was the case because students of the Alliance had approached it largely as a &#13;
policy of the United States government, what, in turn, resulted in a series of conclusions that &#13;
misrepresented the origins of the Alliance for Progress by assigning the wrong relative &#13;
importance to the different factors that played a role in its creation.  &#13;
 &#13;
By redefining the Alliance as what it really was, an inter-American policy, and approaching &#13;
the study of its origins, including its Latin American origins, in the preceding pages I have &#13;
reassessed the origins of the Alliance for Progress. I have shown that, contrary to what it is &#13;
generally believed, the Alliance&#8217;s main purpose was not only or even mainly to prevent the &#13;
spread of communist revolutions and Soviet infiltration in Latin America but to genuinely &#13;
pull the region out of economic, social and political despair.  &#13;
 &#13;
I have also demonstrated that the most important characteristic of the Alliance&#8217;s nature was &#13;
not its magnitude as a foreign aid program but the revolutionary features of its policy &#13;
prescriptions. As a consequence, I have established that the Alliance&#8217;s most important &#13;
conceptual foundation was not a new theory of foreign aid in the United States but the rich, &#13;
sophisticated and influential Latin America structuralist school of thought, which, it is &#13;
important to acknowledge, gained notoriety and augmented its influence by being developed &#13;
in an agency part of the United Nations system. Moreover, even regarding its dimension as a &#13;
major foreign aid program, I have shown that the original idea about the need for a more &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_37" n="37" type="page">
<p>36 &#13;
engaged participation of the United States in inter-American affairs, accompanied by a more &#13;
generous commitment of funds, also originated in Latin America.  &#13;
 &#13;
Without underplaying the key importance of the leadership of the United States, rhetorically, &#13;
politically and particularly economically, all these facts point to the conclusion that the &#13;
Alliance for Progress was much more a child of Latin America than of the United States. It may be too &#13;
late to rename it, as the &#8220;Alliance for Progress&#8221; has become a powerful and symbolic mark. &#13;
Perhaps, in light of this reassessment, we could do justice by referring to it, even in the &#13;
United States, as the Alianza para el Progreso.  &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_38" n="38" type="page">
<p>37 &#13;
Bibliography &#13;
 &#13;
Act of Bogot&#225;. Available from &#13;
http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/intdip/interam/intam08.htm &#13;
 &#13;
Berle, Beatrice Bishop, and Travis Beal Jacobs, ed. Navigating the Rapids 1918-197; &#13;
From the Papers of Adolf A. Berle (New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., &#13;
1973) &#13;
 &#13;
Cabot, John Moors. First Line of Defense: Forty Years&#8217; Experiences of a Career Diplomat.  &#13;
Washington DC: School of Foreign Service, Georgetown University, 1979.  &#13;
 &#13;
Charter of Punta del Este. Available from &#13;
http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/intdip/interam/intam16.htm &#13;
 &#13;
Dillon, C. Douglas. &#8220;The Prelude&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, ed. L. Ronald &#13;
Scheman, 63-66. New York: Praeger, 1988.  &#13;
 &#13;
Dreier, John C, ed. The Alliance for Progress, Problems and Perspectives. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins &#13;
Press, 1962. &#13;
 &#13;
Eisenhower, Milton. &#8220;The Alliance for Progress, Historic Roots&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress, &#13;
Problems and Perspectives, ed. John C. Dreier, 1-23. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press,  &#13;
1962.  &#13;
 &#13;
________. The Wine is Bitter; The United States and Latin America. Garden City: &#13;
Doubleday, 1963. &#13;
 &#13;
Garc&#233;, Adolfo. Ideas y Competencia Pol&#237;tica en Uruguay (1960-1973): Revisando el &#8220;fracaso&#8221; de la  &#13;
CIDE. Montevideo: Ediciones Trilce, 2002.  &#13;
  &#13;
Goodwin, Richard N. Remembering America: A Voice From the Sixties. Boston: Little Brown and  &#13;
Company, 1988. &#13;
 &#13;
Gordon, Lincoln. A New Deal for Latin America: the Alliance for Progress. Cambridge: Harvard &#13;
University Press, 1963.  &#13;
 &#13;
________. &#8220;The Alliance at Birth: Hopes and Fears&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A &#13;
Retrospective, ed. L. Ronald Scheman, 73-79. New York: Praeger, 1988.  &#13;
 &#13;
Pan American Union, Planning for Economic and Social Development for Latin America, &#13;
Washington, D.C., 1961. &#13;
 &#13;
Perloff, Harvey S. Alliance for Progress, A Social Invention in the Making. Baltimore and London: &#13;
The Johns Hopkins Press, 1969.  &#13;
 &#13;
Prebisch, Ra&#250;l. &#8220;Economic Aspects of The Alliance&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress, Problems and &#13;
Perspectives, ed. John C. Dreier, 24-65. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1962.  &#13;
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_39" n="39" type="page">
<p>38 &#13;
 &#13;
Leeds, Roger. &#8220;The Origins of the Alliance for Progress: Continuity and Change in US &#13;
Policy toward Latin America&#8221; Ph.D. diss., Johns Hopkins University, 1976. &#13;
 &#13;
Nixon, Richard M. Six Crises. Garden City, NY: Doubleday &amp; Company, Inc., 1962. &#13;
 &#13;
Scheman, Ronald L., ed. The Alliance for Progress, A Retrospective. New York: Praeger, 1988.  &#13;
 &#13;
________. &#8220;Concept and Creativity&#8221; in The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, ed. L.  &#13;
Ronald Scheman, 3-62. New York: Praeger, 1988.  &#13;
 &#13;
Smith, Gaddis. The Last Years of the Monroe Doctrine: 1945-1993 (New York: Hill and Wang, &#13;
1994) &#13;
 &#13;
Rostow, Walt W. and Max Millikan. A Proposal; Key to an Effective Foreign Policy. New York: &#13;
Harper, 1957. &#13;
 &#13;
________. Eisenhower, Kennedy and Foreign Aid. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1985.  &#13;
 &#13;
Schlesinger, Arthur M. Jr. &#8220;Myth and Reality.&#8221; In The Alliance for Progress; A Retrospective, ed. L. &#13;
Ronald Scheman, 67-72. New York: Praeger, 1988.  &#13;
 &#13;
________. A Thousand Days, John F. Kennedy in the White House. Boston and &#13;
New York: Mariner Books, 2002.  &#13;
 &#13;
Sorensen, Theodore, ed. &#8220;Let the Word Go Forth&#8221; The Speeches, Statements and Writings of John F. &#13;
Kennedy. New York: Delacorte Press, 1988. &#13;
 &#13;
Urquidi, Victor. The Challenge of Development in Latin America. Translated by Marjory Urquidi. &#13;
New York: Praeger, 1964. &#13;
 &#13;
Wiarda, Howard J. &#8220;Did the Alliance &#8216;Lose Its Way,&#8217; or Were Its Assumptions All Wrong &#13;
 from the Beginning and Are Those Assumptions Still with Us?&#8221; in The Alliance for &#13;
 Progress; A Retrospective, ed. L. Ronald Scheman, 95-118. New York: Praeger, 1988.  &#13;
 &#13;
 &#13;
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
