<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>NO TITLE</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>No publication information is avaliable</p>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Produced by: iText 2.1.3 (by lowagie.com)</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Generated from a source PDF document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date>2009-02-17T01:32:55 -0500</date>
</creation>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2009-02-17T04:26:46 -0500</date>
<respStmt>
<name>unknown person</name>
</respStmt>
<item>unknown changes</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 id="page_1" n="1" type="page">
<p>2008; 30: 159&#8211;163
Expanding the reach of health sciences
education and empowering others: the
OpenCourseWare initiative at Tufts University
MARY Y. LEE, SUSAN ALBRIGHT, LISA O&#8217;LEARY, DAWN GERONIMO TERKLA &amp; NANCY WILSON
Tufts University, Medford, MA, USA
Abstract
OpenCourseWare (OCW) represents an innovative and cost-effective opportunity for institutions to take a more active role in
strengthening health sciences education worldwide. OCW content can provide a supplement to curricula available in resource-rich
settings, as well as provide much of the basic content critical to teaching and research in resource-limited health education
environments. Educational institutions worldwide have the opportunity to explore how OCW and other open tools and materials
can supplement efforts to build health education capacity to address global shortages of healthcare workers. Tufts University has
worked to leverage open, digital resources to support medical education since 1994 with the creation of the Tufts University
Sciences Knowledgebase (TUSK). This experience has yielded vital lessons for institutions interested in OCW, including:
effectively motivating faculty participation; managing the inherent complexity of open publishing of health sciences content due to
its rapidly evolving nature and reliance on copyrighted materials; generating support through internal and external communication
throughout the process; and creating institutional systems that ensure the long-term sustainability of OCW initiatives.
Introduction
OpenCourseWare (OCW) comprises &#8216;&#8216;free and open digital
publication of high quality educational materials, organized as
courses,&#8217;&#8217; capitalizing on the Internet&#8217;s potential to minimize
obstacles (e.g., borders and geographic distance) to the free
exchange of knowledge and new ideas (OpenCourseWare
Consortium 2007). Unlike distance learning programs that
charge tuition and limit participation, OCW offers unlimited
access to course materials to anyone with an internet
connection (Atkins et al. 2007). Educators from around the
world can augment their syllabi; students can enhance their
coursework or pursue self study; and the general public can
browse through the curricula at leading universities and
benefit from reading lists and lectures.
When considering the impact of OCW on medical
education internationally, it is important to note that OCW,
as a source of course content, represents only one component
of health sciences education. In practice, medical education
requires a complex blend of educational materials, experiential
learning, and human interaction within a school structure. The
significance of OCW in a resource-rich setting is likely to differ
greatly from a resource-limited environment &#8211; the former may
view OCW primarily as a welcome supplement to existing
strong curricula, whereas the latter may view OCW as filling
critical gaps in core content (Keats 2003). As we face a global
health crisis rooted in an international shortage of healthcare
workers and an aging population burdened with acute and
chronic diseases exacerbated by climate change and conflict
(Garrett 2007; Gostin 2007), Tufts has embraced OCW as an
open model for mobilizing faculty across nations to leverage
their expertise to build a shared educational infrastructure and
learning network. This paper outlines the development of
OCW at Tufts University, explores the impact of openly
Practice points
. Developing high-quality OCW content for the health
sciences is an inherently complex and faculty-intensive
process due to the content&#8217;s density, rapidly evolving
and specialized nature, and heavy reliance on newly
published third-party materials.
. Making high-quality content available in resource-
limited environments can have a significant impact on
faculty and learners by leveraging invaluable faculty
time, filling critical gaps in basic curriculum content, and
allowing for local customization.
. Recruiting faculty contributors for voluntary OCW
initiatives requires tapping into altruistic drivers and
providing reinforcement through ongoing communica-
tion and engagement with the broader &#8216;&#8216;open&#8217;&#8217;
community.
. Institutionalizing OCW initiatives into the normal work-
flow, budget, and infrastructure of the hosting organiza-
tion is key to enabling their long-term sustainability.
. Revolutionizing global access to quality health sciences
education requires institutions to rethink their role in
education and examine the opportunities and obliga-
tions presented by participating in increasingly open
learning systems.
Correspondence: Dr. Mary Y. Lee, Associate Provost, Tufts University, Ballou Hall, 1st Floor, 1 The Green, Medford MA, 02176, USA. Tel: 617-627-
4733; fax: 617-627-3950; email: mary.lee@tufts.edu
ISSN 0142&#8211;159X print/ISSN 1466&#8211;187X online/08/020159&#8211;5 C223 2008 Informa UK Ltd. 159
DOI: 10.1080/01421590701881665
Downloaded By: [Tufts University] At: 18:32 17 February 2009
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_2" n="2" type="page">
<p>sharing doctoral-level medical and other health sciences
content, and summarizes the associated lessons for institutions
interested in participating in OCW.
Background
Tufts OCW should be considered within the broader context of
the Open Education Resources (OER) movement. OER can
include open content, tools, or infrastructure (OECD 2007).
Tufts has been engaging in OER work for more than a decade,
with the majority of efforts related to the development of the
Tufts University Sciences Knowledgebase (TUSK) (Albright
et al. 1999; Metz et al. 2001; Lee et al. 2003,). TUSK is a
integrated digital repository and curriculum knowledge
management and delivery system used by Tufts&#8217; four health
sciences schools, and other health sciences institutions in
India, Tanzania, Uganda, Kenya, and the United States. The
TUSK infrastructure, developed largely from open source
software, can be utilized by any institution to create, import,
manage, search, and customize fully integrated curricula, and
was Tufts&#8217; first major step toward developing open resources
to help meet global needs in medical education. Many of Tufts&#8217;
faculty have been teaching and conducting field research in
the developing world over the past decade, and the TUSK
system is increasingly being used to support their work.
OpenCourseWare, as a subset of open content within OER,
was launched by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology
(MIT) in 1999 as an initiative with the goals of providing free,
searchable access to MIT&#8217;s course material for the general
public and expanding the reach of the OCW concept (Carson
2004). In 2002, UNESCO organized the &#8216;&#8216;Forum on the Impact
of Open Courseware for Higher Education in Developing
Countries,&#8217;&#8217; which was attended by representatives of
universities from both developed and developing countries
(UNESCO 2002). At this conference, the term &#8216;&#8216;open education
resource&#8217;&#8217; was more clearly defined as &#8216;&#8216;the open provision
of educational resources, enabled by information and
communication technologies, for consultation, use, and
adaptation by a community of users for non-commercial
purposes&#8217;&#8217; (Hylen 2005).
When Tufts was invited to join MIT in its OpenCourseWare
initiative in 2004, the institution&#8217;s expertise in the health
sciences and international policy complemented MIT&#8217;s
strengths in engineering and science, and Tufts&#8217; track record
of creating an extensive body of digital materials and tools
to support healthcare education made Tufts a ready partner.
Tufts OCW launched in June 2005 as a University-wide
initiative, with six courses from three of its four health sciences
schools. At the time of this writing, Tufts&#8217; OCW site now
houses 38 courses, including nearly half of the School of
Medicine&#8217;s didactic curriculum.
Tufts&#8217; partnership with MIT and other early participants in
the OCW movement has evolved into the OpenCourseWare
Consortium (OCWC), an organization with more than 100
member universities and associated institutions dedicated to
advancing education and empowering learners through OCW.
Expanding our existing OER work into OCW has allowed
Tufts to add high-quality health sciences content to the global
OCW inventory. This &#8216;&#8216;match&#8217;&#8217; between open sharing and
the values of the institution was critical to gaining support from
administrators and faculty for the OCW initiative, which soon
became a highly visible embodiment of those values.
Tufts OCW goals and usage
Two goals have been central to the Tufts OCW project: (l) to
share Tufts&#8217; rich content globally, particularly in the health
sciences, with learners and teachers in ways that encourage
development of locally relevant and customized resources,
and (2) to measure the impact of the initiative in a systematic
way. Assessing the use of OCW resources and understanding
its impact within the Tufts community and beyond was an
important principle of the initial program design. The success
of the OCW project needed to be measured not just by the
number of courses produced, but rather by defining all
meaningful metrics for success. Experts from the Tufts&#8217; Office
of Institutional Research and Evaluation have been active
members of the Tufts OCW Steering Committee and the Tufts
OCW working group through every phase of the project. From
the program&#8217;s pilot phase, a longitudinal data collection
protocol was established as a key component of the project
to capture critical information that would facilitate the
evaluation of the impact and usability of Tufts OCW. The
evaluation plan was designed to continually assess the
initiative&#8217;s success in achieving its objectives through an
intercept survey, web analytics, and analysis of the qualitative
feedback provided by the users, contributing faculty members,
and OCW staff. This information has been routinely analysed
and summarized to allow for continuous monitoring, process
changes, and ongoing development of the site.
Usage of the Tufts OCW site has grown steadily since its
initial release. Evaluators have examined the characteristics of
users, their reasons for visiting the website, and their
evaluations of the initiative. To date, the typical user profile
is highly educated (holding a doctoral degree, 25%; master&#8217;s
degree, 30%; or bachelor&#8217;s degree, 26%); primarily interested
in graduate-level medical or health sciences education; and
either affiliated with an educational institution as a student
(20%) or faculty (over 20%), or identified as a self-learner (over
50%). The majority of users (60%) are from the United States,
with greatest international representation from Asia and
Western Europe. Students cite use of materials to complement
courses in which they are currently enrolled, or to enhance
personal knowledge. Faculty access the website to develop or
plan a curriculum, prepare to teach a specific class, or learn
about a subject matter to enhance learning or research. The
remaining users are &#8216;&#8216;self-learners&#8217;&#8217; who report visiting the site
to enhance personal knowledge or to maintain currency in
their professional fields.
Lessons learned
The past two years of Tufts&#8217; OCW site development have
yielded lessons that may be useful to other institutions
considering joining the OCW initiative, particularly in the
area of health sciences. Specific lessons arose from dealing
with issues related to startup, faculty recruitment, copyright
and content, and communications.
M. Y. Lee et al.
160
Downloaded By: [Tufts University] At: 18:32 17 February 2009
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_3" n="3" type="page">
<p>Infrastructure, staffing, and
financial support
With more than a decade to mature into a comprehensive
curriculum management and delivery system using metadata-
tagged XML-based content and multimedia content, TUSK
provided a sound technical platform upon which to build
OCW. Even though the initial Tufts OCW effort required
creating a parallel system, tools to move content from TUSK to
OCW, and an open, copyright-cleared subset of existing
materials, using the TUSK platform with fully digitized
materials allowed the OCW project to become established
much more efficiently. While current courses presented
on Tufts OCW represent only some of what is available
internally on TUSK, the remaining core content is being
systematically converted into the OCW format by TUSK
staff. Funding and staff time were also critical inputs to a
successful start-up, as well as considerable external funding
(see acknowledgements).
Faculty recruitment and involvement are essential for
building OCW content. In an environment where faculty
participation in OCW is entirely voluntary, it was important to
understand faculty motivations for contributing. The drivers
were largely altruistic with participants citing their desire to
share knowledge with areas of the world with limited
resources, to contribute to their disciplines (see also
Johnstone 2005), and to increase the reputation of the
institution. Raising awareness of the OCW activity internally
was important, as was the support of key faculty and
administrators, including the deans, provost, and president.
Senior members of the OCW team have met regularly with
academic deans of each of Tufts&#8217; schools and have attended
faculty meetings to present the OCW initiative and answer
questions. Identifying faculty concerns early in the process and
taking proactive steps to address those concerns must be an
institutional priority for universities building OCW sites.
Specific faculty concerns regarding Tufts&#8217; OCW initiative
were identified through a study conducted by Tufts&#8217; Office of
Institutional Research and Evaluation to solicit faculty opinions
and reactions throughout the pilot phase of the initiative.
Although the overall results demonstrated that faculty had
positive experiences and recognized the value of OCW to both
the institution and the wider community, some faculty initially
had questions about having to exclude much copyrighted
materials that added substantial value to their original course.
Some felt that the relative bareness of the initial OCW course
(compared with the richness of the internal TUSK materials)
made the course seem rudimentary and could devalue their
reputations. Other concerns included the time commitment
required, loss of control over materials, possible violation of
privacy by users attempting to contact them, and effect on their
academic credentials and promotion.
The results of follow-up interviews conducted in the fall
of 2005 revealed that these concerns had faded. Only one
faculty member reported being contacted by an OCW user,
and it was a positive interaction. Faculty members had
adjusted to their materials being openly available. Despite
some initial skepticism about the value of the project to the
University and to users, the faculty participating in the
follow-up interviews clearly recognized the merit of the
initiative. Although the interviews were conducted early in
the launch of Tufts OCW, faculty members already understood
the connection of the project to the University&#8217;s mission to
extend its reach internationally and to foster contributions to
civil society.
Several lessons based on this feedback were helpful in later
interactions with contributing faculty. OCW staff has learned to
provide regular communication about the project, its goals,
and the project&#8217;s connection to the broader international OCW
community. The initial orientation to the project and on-going
communication about the project&#8217;s progress as courses are
being added addresses concerns that materials were being
well-handled. Regular communication about the project to the
broader Tufts community, including statistics verifying global
use with highly positive user feedback, emphasizes faculty
members&#8217; roles within a growing &#8216;&#8216;open&#8217;&#8217; community and
helps foster cross-disciplinary connections between faculty
that reinforces altruistic motivations. Winning the support of
leaders within the faculty and administration and sharing
specific steps taken to address issues such as faculty time
and copyright questions are important to launching a
successful process.
Copyright and content
complexity issues
While there are few technical issues involved in converting
the courses developed within TUSK for OCW, one major
barrier to rapid publication is the labor required to verify
compliance with copyright law. United States copyright law
includes a fair use provision. Fair use means that if certain
criteria are met, copyrighted materials may be used without
prior permission. These provisions include examining the
nature and amount of material used, as well as its commercial
impact. Since health sciences faculty members commonly
and legitimately include extensive copyrighted material in
their lectures and textbook-sized syllabi within the Tufts
environment, a judgment must be made about copyright
infringement for each piece of third-party content used
before publication externally through OCW. These page-by-
page and image-by-image reviews by faculty and staff are
painstaking and time consuming (up to 150 hours per course),
and must be taken into account both when planning staffing
and workflow, and setting realistic targets of the number of
courses that can be published within a given timeframe.
To minimize copyright problems, Tufts staff found it critical
to educate faculty early in the course creation process about
utilizing resources in the public domain wherever possible.
Tufts&#8217; librarians have played a key role in educating faculty
about copyright issues and helping to identify open alter-
natives to copyrighted sources. Staff members are responsible
for contacting copyright owners for permission to use material,
helping to locate open materials, and assisting faculty in
developing their own materials. Despite staff help, faculty can
still feel overburdened by the sheer volume of lecture and
syllabi material that must be reviewed. Faculty in the process
of new course creation are now coached on the benefits of
using open resources, the importance of having full citations
The OpenCourseWare initiative at Tufts University
161
Downloaded By: [Tufts University] At: 18:32 17 February 2009
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_4" n="4" type="page">
<p>imbedded in course materials, and the advantages of
collaboration with professional librarians to identify such
resources early in the process.
The OCW courses are made available under a Creative
Commons public license (for more information on Creative
Commons, see Ellaway and Martin in this edition of Medical
Teacher). Certain restrictions dealing with the use of the
University name in connection with materials and exemptions
that would require the user to seek permission to use certain
third-party materials are noted in the policy statement on the
website. Faculty members at Tufts own the copyright to their
courses, and earlier reservations about ownership after open
publishing have essentially disappeared. Faculty who have
contributed courses thus far have not expressed any reluctance
to grant Tufts University use of course materials as OCW.
Communication
Limited global awareness of OCW has precluded widespread
use, particularly within the health sciences community.
Despite this fact, the University is optimistic that knowledge
will spread over time. While Tufts&#8217; external promotion of OCW
has been modest, the site continues to receive traffic via
Google, the OCWC, the OER Commons, and other search
engines. Participation in these organizations is a valuable tool
for universities to increase the visibility of their OCW sites.
The global language barrier across OCW sites is minimized
in human medical sciences where English is the international
language for research and most education. The language
limitation for using other OCW materials world-wide seems
likely to improve. Groups in Spain and Asia, for example,
have begun the process of translating some courses from
participating OCW institutions into local languages including
Spanish and both simplified and traditional Chinese. To date,
eighteen Tufts courses have been partially translated into
Chinese. Concerns about the accuracy of the translations have
been mitigated by the ability of users to view the original and
translated versions simultaneously via a split screen. However,
as the network of institutions and individuals that are
broadening the accessibility of OCW grows, the OCW
initiative will have to rely on some systematic quality control
mechanisms if it is to achieve its goals fully.
Sustainability
Tufts OCW remains an important component of the
University&#8217;s broader efforts in OER, reinforcing Tufts&#8217; commit-
ment to share its assets with the wider world. The University is
developing long-term strategies to ensure that its full range of
OER efforts is sustainable. The sustainability of open resources
is tied not only to an institutional &#8216;&#8216;culture fit&#8217;&#8217; but also to
identifying stable funding sources that allow for continued
development and maintenance, as well as technical and
content support once initial grant funding ends (Downes
2007). To address this, Tufts is slowly incorporating its range of
OER initiatives into the normal workflow, function, and budget
of the institution, while continuing to seek outside funding for
related research and development of new projects.
Next steps
The participation of health sciences educators in the OER
movement presents the opportunity to shape how information
is generated, used, and shared for the benefit of future
generations of healthcare workers, particularly those in the
developing world. National and international groups are
developing best practices and open standards that are essential
for exchanging content and tools effectively across cultures
and technical platforms. Quality control, particularly for health
sciences content due to its rapidly evolving and highly
complex nature, creates the opportunity for leading experts
in their fields to unite and form international &#8216;&#8216;editorial boards&#8217;&#8217;
to ensure the accuracy of a core subset of open content that
any school could confidently use to create a locally customized
core curriculum. Expanding the impact of OCW for health
sciences education will require the development of innovative
tools such as semantic searching and competency-based
learning and assessment tools that are linked to content. We
are in a new era where the blurring of formal and informal
learning, and the blurring of teacher and learner (OECD 2007),
will compel institutions to reassess their role in education and
examine the opportunities provided by participating in an
increasingly open model of learning for international health
sciences education. Tufts is eager to contribute to this
progressively interconnected global community and to the
inevitable debates about how best to harness the power of
open learning for the empowerment of all.
Acknowledgements
To fund projects and staff needed for specific OCW content
development and tool creation, Tufts OCW has received
generous support from The William and Flora Hewlett
Foundation, a welcome supplement to initial funds from the
Kurtz Family Foundation, the Jonathan M. Tisch College of
Citizenship and Public Service at Tufts, and Tufts University.
Notes on contributors
MARY Y. LEE, M.D., is Associate Provost of Tufts University.
SUSAN ALBRIGHT is Executive Director of the Tufts University Sciences
Knowledgebase (TUSK) project at Tufts University.
LISA O&#8217;LEARY is Assistant Director of Institutional Research and Evaluation
at Tufts University, and is pursuing her Ph.D. at Boston University.
DAWN GERONIMO TERKLA, Ph.D., is Executive Director of Institutional
Research and Evaluation at Tufts University.
NANCY WILSON, M.B.A., is Director and Associate Dean of the Jonathan
M. Tisch College of Citizenship and Public Service at Tufts University.
References
Albright SA, Eaton EK, Alkasab T. 1999. Tufts Health Sciences Library and
Medical School Collaborative Virtual Medical Library (In Progress).
Acad Med 74:575.
Atkins DE, Brown JS, Hammond AL. 2007. A review of the Open
Educational Resources (OER) Movement: Achievements, challenges,
and new opportunities (California, A Report to The William and Flora
Hewlett Foundation).
M. Y. Lee et al.
162
Downloaded By: [Tufts University] At: 18:32 17 February 2009
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_5" n="5" type="page">
<p>Carson, S. 2004. &#8216;&#8216;MIT Open Courseware Program Evaluation Findings,
Summary Report,&#8217;&#8217; March. Available online at: http://www.myoops.org/
twocw/mit/NR/rdonlyres/250BF523-3FA0-49AB-A78B-C6633D6E666A/
0/Program_Summary_March_2004.pdf
Downes S. 2007. Models for sustainable open resources. Interdisciplinary
J Knowl Learn Objects 3:27&#8211;44.
Eaton, E., Albright, S. 2000. Tufts&#8217; Digital Curriculum: Cause and Effect of
Converging Vision, Proceedings of the 8th International Congress on
Medical Librarianship, London, England, July 2&#8211;5, 2000.
Garrett L. 2007. The Challenge of Global Health. Foreign Affairs 86:14&#8211;28.
Gostin LO. 2007. Meeting the Survival Needs of the World&#8217;s Least Healthy
People: A Proposed Model for Global Health Governance. J Am Med
Assoc 298:225&#8211;228.
Hylen, J. (2006). Open Educational Resources: Opportunities and
Challenges. Report from OECD&#8217;s Centre for Educational Research
and Innovation. Available online at: http://www.oercommons.org/
matters/open-educational-resources-opportunities-and-challenges.
(accessed 15 July 2007).
Johnstone SM. 2005. Open Educational Resources Serve the World.
Educause Quart 3:15&#8211;18.
Keats, D. 2003. Collaborative development of open content: A
process model to unlock the potential for African uni-
versities. First Monday, 8(2). Available online at: http://
firstmonday.org/issues/issue8_2/keats/index.html (accessed June
2003).
Lee MY, Albright SA, Alkasab T, Damassa DA, Wang PJ, Eaton EK. 2003.
Tufts&#8217; Health Sciences Database: Lessons, Issues, and Opportunities.
Acad Med 78:254&#8211;264.
Metz, B., Lee, MY., Albright, S., Alkasab, T. 2001. Transforming Medical and
Health Science Education At Tufts University. Educause Quart
November 4, 2001.
National Institutes for Health. 2007. Information on the Unified Medical
Language System http://umlsinfo.nlm.nih.gov/
OECD.. 2007. Giving Knowledge for Free: The Emergence of Open
Educational Resources (Paris, OECD).
OpenCourseWare Consortium. (2007). Website. Available online at:
http://www.ocwconsortium.org (accessed March 2007).
UNESCO. (2002). Forum on the Impact of Open Courseware for Higher
Education in Developing Countries. (Paris, 1&#8211;3 July 2002. Paris:
UNESCO).
The OpenCourseWare initiative at Tufts University
163
Downloaded By: [Tufts University] At: 18:32 17 February 2009
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
